<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The instruction of a Christian man, in vertue and honestie.].</title>
            <author>Hoper, R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14089</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843000</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176849</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240897739</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 13766.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S107298</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99843000e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14089)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176849)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 713:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The instruction of a Christian man, in vertue and honestie.].</title>
                  <author>Hoper, R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6+], 136 [i.e. 146], [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>H. Bynneman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R. Hoper's name from leaf A3r.</note>
                  <note>Title from caption title, leaf A6r.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of a vertuous or honest life.</note>
                  <note>With an index.</note>
                  <note>Page numbers 71-146 misnumbered 61-136 in page numbering.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 14106a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks all before leaf A3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:3"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>about it. Thus desiring the Lorde to encrease dayly in you the giftes of his heauenly grace, of worshippe also and health (both of body and minde) that you may still perseuer and goe on forwardes in such onely things as are accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hys holy will: whyche, that you may in deede so doe, I humbly beseeche hym to gyue vnto you abundaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of his holy Spirite. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Seruaunt. R. HOPER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:4"/>
            <head>A Prayer to be saide in the Morning.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Heauenly father I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto thee most har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye thanckes, that thou hast mercifully vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed to preserue mee this night passed: besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee also in like manner, that thou wilte this whole daye following moste gratiously preserue mee vnto the glory and laude of thy holye name, and to the saluation of my Soule. And thou which arte the onely true lighte, and knowest thereof no going downe, and which arte the eternall Sunne, whiche quickneth, nourisheth, and refresheth all thinges: I beseeche thee (with thy clearenesse) to shine into my hearte and minde, leaste (at anye tyme) I waxe ouer grosse in sin: but by thy holy direction, I may attaine vnto euerlastyng life. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:4"/>
            <head>¶ The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Actantius Firmianus,</hi> in his second booke of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Institutions doth say, that man, after all things in the worlde were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, was lastly formed and made, affirming this: And God would not bring man into this world, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till suche time, as all things for him were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. And holy Scriptures also teache, howe man was the laste worke of GOD whiche hee wrought: and so brought into the world, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an house nowe already prepared, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly furnished: and also for whose sake all things therein were made. The whiche thing, Ethnicke Poets do witnesse: as <hi>Ouid</hi> (who hathe spoken of the worlde, and of all thinges whiche were created) sayeth thus of man: A more diuine creature than these, and more capable of the highest minde, as yet was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, whiche should haue rule vppon all other things, that is to saye, Man, formed of God for the same purpose, to be a Ruler and a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor, and a King also ouer all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:176849:5"/> and Gods Vicegerent heere on the earth. For it behoueth, that firste of all be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects and a Kingdome, beefore that a King be constituted and appointed. If Man therefore be a King, it behoueth him to knowr and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande his Natiuitie, Rule, Mighte, and Nobilitie, as Hystoriographers commonlye write of Kings. Man is borne of a moste noble Parent, to wit, euen of God himselfe, and of the slyme of the earth, to the ende he should not be forgetfull, or ouer proude. And after that hee was created concerning his owne body, GOD gaue also vnto him a woman, which he should loue euen as hymselfe. For, God his Father did knowe, that it was not good for Man to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Manne was borne or broughte into the worlde, but bare and naked, that hee mighte clothe hymselfe, not onely with wooll or linnen garments, but also to bee apparelled with the comely vesture of Vertue. Againe, Man is not borne hairie after the manner of beastes, to the end he shoulde bee gentle and milde, &amp; not cruel or sauage: for haire growing on the bodie, plainely foresheweth or declareth a fierce or mercilesse minde. Man also is borne but with a weake and a feeble body, that hee
<pb facs="tcp:176849:5"/> shoulde not truste in his own strength, as beasts do: but rather to desire helpe and aide of God: and yet notwithstanding hee is ordayned and appoynted a King ouer all strong and mightye Beastes. This King therefore I say, hath noble and princely giftes, by the which he excelleth al other creatures: for he hath another maner of forme than other beastes haue. For brute beastes haue a forme yeelding and bowing downe to the Earth: but Man hath his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce erected vp towardes the Starres (or vp to the Heauens) that he shoulde despise as vaine, all earthly thinges, and so muche the more loue heauenly things: and might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with also thinke, that in respecte of his moste excellent forme, he ought otherwise to liue, thā as the maner is of Beastes. Moreouer, Kinges haue also their Councellors, whose aduise and councelles they vse wisely to follow, euen in the tyme of the friendly banquetting of thēselues. And they haue also their <hi>Caesar,</hi> vnto whom they are compelled to yeelde an accompte of their Stewardeship or Gouernment: For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise they are reiected from their Kingdome. Euen so likewise vnto Man, who is a King of worldly things, is Reason giuē, as a noble Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour:
<pb facs="tcp:176849:6"/> whose aduice and councell if hee shall folow, he shall bothe wisely gouerne hymselfe, and also all other earthly creatures. It behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth likewise the King to bee prudent in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, that he neither offend subiects, nor yet his Councellors and Courtiers: and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetely to moderate the bridle of Regiment: leaste complaintes be made of hym vnto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar</hi> (or vnto the mightie Emperour) that the Prouince is spoiled: Euen so it behoueth Man (who is a King ouer all worldly things) to bee prouident and wise in vsing things created for hym: specially also an other man who is hys neighboure: vnto whome it is graunted to be of like forme, speache, and reason, and to haue alwayes a care howe he may please <hi>Caesar</hi> his God: that he may long rule well his kingdome: &amp; in the ende obteyne that rewarde which is perpetuall &amp; vnexpressable. And how heerein hee oughte honestly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue hymselfe, these precepts following shall plainly shewe vnto hym.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176849:6"/>
            <head>¶ The Instruction of a Christian man, in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Honestie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>What an honest life is, whereof it consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth, and what it profiteth. <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas, after al things were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, Man was borne into the world, as it were the Gouernoure and Moderatour of al things, and a Bailiffe also ordained of God: he must then of righte so liue, that he may please hys founder Almightie God: that being once called backe by death of his Patrō, like as Princes are called of their <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sars,</hi> into his heauenly Palaice, may giue an accompte of hys Stewardship, and of his rule and Gouernement. And that hée may thus do indéede, he hath great néede of an accepted, very noble, princely, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176849:7"/> honest life.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>Vhat a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And to knowe what is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest life, you shall vnderstande, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, than for a mā, by his life and conuersation, far to passe and surmount the life of very brutishe &amp; senselesse bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes: And as muche as by nature maye be performed, he ought to haue in hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe such a life of true holinesse, as is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lyke vnto God himselfe: whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in no other thing, than in the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gift of Vertue.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>Vhat Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e is.</note> And Vertue truely is nothing else, but to flye from vices, and to folowe Godlinesse and Honestie: For it is the office and end of vertue. Sainct Augustine witnesseth, that an honest &amp; pleasante life to God, consisteth in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, saying, that the Art to liue wel, was nothing else but Vertue. And <hi>Baptista Mantuanus</hi> expresseth what Vertue is in these words (Vertue speaking of hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe after this maner:) I am (saith Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue) the gouernor of Fortune, and the whip of Wickednesse: and that I may defende men, I cast downe the Towers of Hell, that I may bring them safe into the habitation of Saints. My knowlege
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176849:7"/> exhorteth men to the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and to God also himselfe: yea, and sheweth the way, by the which men goe vp to the Sky: I make the iourny plain: I am the steppe and right trace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Fathers went to Heauen: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the auntient Fathers soughte for the Dore of the greate God, whereas are Ryuers of Milke running wyth moste flourishing pastures. I know no delight: and I and deceitful Pleasure be always at variaunce: and from the one side of the Realme to the other I stande at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie against al Vices. I haue much strife amongst contrarie things: for I haue many enemies, euen within mine owne Kingdome. Continuall laboure maketh me strong: and ydlenesse much enféebleth me. And as ofte as persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on commeth, I am not thereof afraide, but stande vnto it, and that manfullye: for I knowe not howe to be ouercome, nor in what maner to yéelde. And if at any time Aduersitie assaileth me, I still take it patiently: I instructe Man also &amp; teache him within fewe yeares by sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176849:8"/> cares, to be made like vnto God: and at length I carry him aboue the Stars: I haue tamed the sauage and wilde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of men:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>talius,</hi> is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> svveete <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>Vell, running <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t of the hill <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>nassus.</hi>
                  </note> I am the Well of <hi>Casta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius:</hi> and I am the Lady of Knowledge and Manhoode. Manye more names I haue, but yet the same thing. I am not consumed with sicknesse, nor worne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye with yeares: I remaine sincere, still flourishing &amp; immortall. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Globes with their motions, can doe nothing agaynste mée: the Starres with their glistering Beames, neither yet the Sunne with his lighte can haue any force againste me. Therefore after the proofe and truste of so greate works, I am yet forsaken: I wander abroad in vnknown coasts, and am altogither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and caste off for naught. My cause wanteth a Defēdor, bycause mens hearts be full of deceit, pride puffing vp their mindes: and Wickednesse dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth loftie and highe officers with it: Watchmen are but slenderly estéemed, and inquisition and search defendeth the bordures and entrances of the Realme:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176849:8"/> Religion lyeth despised, and the worship of God goeth away with contempt. And nowe doth wanne and very pale Faith, go in a torne and ragged coate, and very much stumbleth, by reason of his weake and féeble féete. The Maiestie of good Lawes is vtterly destroyed: godly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners be assalted with many cruel Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters: Honestie is ouersilent and holdeth his peace: and al shamefastnesse is quite banished awaye. But God truely séeth it, and will weygh all thinges in a iuste Ballaunce: and when time shal require, he wil bring mée againe into mine own Kingdome.</p>
               <q>Oh, would God it were his pleasure euen so to do, now in this oure moste sinful and gracelesse age.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarchus</hi> also more plainly expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth what Vertue teacheth, describing it vnder the name of Philosophie, in hys booke <hi>Of the Education of Children,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, that by it wée knowe what is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, and what is dishonest: what is iust,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176849:9"/> and vniuste: what is to be chosen, and what is to be auoyded: in what sorte we must vse our Parentes, how our elders, how Straungers, howe Officers, howe Friendes, howe Wiues, and how Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes: and how and in what manner it behooueth vs to worshippe God, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our Parentes, to reuerence our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to obey the Lawes, to giue place to Magistrates, and to loue our friends. Amongest Women, we must kéepe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie, we muste tender our children, and not be seruile with seruauntes: and that whiche is moste of al, not to be puffed vp in wealth, or ouermuche reioise in pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, neyther yet to be deiected or sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull in trouble and aduersitie, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to be giuen to bodily pleasures, ne yet to put vpon vs the mindes of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes when we be moued to anger (whose nature is to be fierce and cruel:) but it is mans part to make much of Mildnesse, of Courtesie, and Godlinesse.</p>
               <q>The Poet also <hi>Lucillius</hi> thus describeth Ʋertue.</q>
               <p>It is a Vertue (saith he) <hi>Albinus,</hi> to pay
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176849:9"/> euery man that which is due vnto him: to doe good vnto those amongest whome we here liue and are conuersante.</p>
               <p>It is a Vertue to know that whiche euery thing importeth. It is a Vertue for a man to know that whiche is iuste, profitable, and honest: what things are good, what things are euill: and what is also vnprofitable, filthie and vnhonest. It is a Vertue also, to pay for that wée take. It is a Vertue to knowe the ende and measure in séeking of substāce. Yea, and it is also a Vertue to giue vnto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor that whiche in very déede is due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to honor. Vertue is an enimie and an aduersarie vnto men of euill disposition and maners: and on the other side, it is the defendor of all men in their good bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour and maners. It maketh muche of all these, and wisheth well to all, and liueth friendly with all men. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, it mindeth his Countries commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and profite, and thinketh it more deare vnto him than his Parentes: and laste of all, his owne state of welfare.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:176849:10"/>
                  <head>The diuision of Vertue.</head>
                  <p>ACcording to <hi>Cicero</hi> in his first booke of Offices, there are foure Vertues, out of whiche, all others doe issue, and from whence all honestie commeth: that is to wit,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ence.</note> Prudence, Iustice, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and Fortitude. Of whiche there are foure diuers Duties, as <hi>Macrobius</hi> witnesseth in his booke of <hi>Caius Scipio</hi> his Dreame: who ascribeth these duties or offices vnto thē, saying on this wise: It is the part of Prudēce, both to know and learn, how al things are to be done: to desire nothing saue onely that whiche is iuste, neither to do any thing by anye action of man: but to foresée things with an heauenly witte: to prouide for daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to come, and to beware timely of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>tude.</note>And it is the office of Fortitude, not to feare any daungers, or to be afraid of any thing, saue onelye all those thinges whiche be dishonest: and with a valiant courage to suffer both in aduersitie and in prosperitie.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:176849:10"/>
                  <p>The office of Temperance is,<note place="margin">Temperan<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire nothing whereof wée maye after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes repent, and in nothing to passe the law of meane and measure: and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the yoke of Reason to tame the vice of Couetousnes, Modestie, Bashfulnes, Abstinence, Chastitie, Honestie, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate spending, Sobernesse, and Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastnesse do al waite vppon Tēperance.</p>
                  <p>The parte of Iustice is, to kéepe, and giue vnto euery man,<note place="margin">Iustice.</note> that whiche is his owne. Of Iustice commeth these Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that is to say, Innocencie, Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe, Vnitie, Godlinesse, Religion, Affection and Gentlenesse. <hi>Cicero</hi> in the firste booke of his Offices, sayeth: The firste of Iustice is, that no man doe hurt one another: Secondely, that wée vse thinges whiche are common, as thinges common: and things that are proper, as our owne. The foundation of al Iustice, is Faith: that is, the accomplishement truly of all sayings and couenauntes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his sixte Booke, sayeth,<note place="margin">Lactantius.</note> that the office of Iustice is of two sorts. The firste is ioyned togither with God
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176849:11"/> by Religion. The seconde, with man by mercie and courtesie. By these two ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues (saieth <hi>Macrobius</hi>) a good manne is made, first of all, a gouernor of himselfe, then of his friends, and then of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, iustly and prudently gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things belonging vnto menne, not forsaking the thinges belonging vnto God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the reward of Vertue and honest life.</head>
                  <p>IF any man be desirous to séek out y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> office &amp; reward of Vertue and of an honest life, let hym know, that the office therof is double: that is, first, to blesse, or to make a man blessed after death: &amp; in this life to be made like to God. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ilius.</note>
                     <hi>Virgilius</hi> right well did sing: Few are there, whom iust Iupiter loueth: or else, whom feruent Vertue hathe brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte vp vnto Heauen. Or according to <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his sixte Booke:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>antius.</note> The office (saith he) of Vertue is, to refraine from Anger, to auoide Couetousnesse, and to bridle Luste. Secondly, she maketh hir
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176849:11"/> foster childe to bée indéede moste plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of all good things, whereby he shall not haue néede of any thing, but to haue store of al things: as <hi>Plautus</hi> witnesseth,<note place="margin">Plautus.</note> saying: Thus Vertue truely passeth all other thinges: for libertie, health, life, substance, parentes, and children, are all by hir defended and kepte safe. Vertue is suche a thing, that it contayneth all things in it selfe. Al good things are sent vnto him, in whome Vertue beareth the sway. Vertue is desirous of no common rewarde, or to haue that which is giuen of all men: neyther yet of honoure, or of glorie, as <hi>Sillius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sillius.</note> the Poet recordeth: Vertue indéede it selfe is a moste beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and faire reward, euen vnto it selfe. To whome, <hi>Claudianus</hi> the Poet allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in these verses: Vertue indéede it selfe farre shining aboue Fortune, is a treasure sufficient and good ynoughe for itselfe. Vertue is not aduanced with the roddes of Triumphe and Victorie: it séeketh not to bée made famous by the well liking of people: it coueteth no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde helpe or ayde, and it hath no néed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176849:12"/> of praise. When fortune most fauoureth hir, then is she moste constant: she stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fixed and immoueable at chaunces: and from the heigth of hir princelye and famous Tower, shée despiseth all vaine and worldly thyngs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Horatius.</head>
                  <p>VErtue knoweth no vncleane or fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie repulse: she alwayes clearelye glistereth and brightly shineth, when she is in moste base estate and honour. Shee neyther desireth goodes nor riches for a rewarde, bicause she is farre more noble and excellent than they: as <hi>Horace</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ce.</note> Siluer (sayeth he) is worse than Golde: and Golde is worse than Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>robius.</note> Therefore <hi>Macrobius</hi> sayeth in hys Booke of <hi>Scipio</hi> his Dreame: the wise man setleth both the fruite and reward of Vertue in his conscience: but a foole setleth it in glorie. And <hi>Macrobius</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the same place, that if any manne desire to bée made perfecte or sounde in Vertue: Let him content hymselfe with the rewarde of his own conscience: that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176849:12"/> is to saye, that it bée well instructed in vertues, and to séeke for no further praise.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>How an honest life and Vertue are to be gotten. CHAP. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that desi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth to get an honest life and Vertue, hath need of .ij. things. Firste, that hee do so prep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nde, that it may alwayes be worthy of Vertue and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nestie. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that he also learne (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s mind is prepared) how to gette V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtue. The readinesse of the minde oughte to be done by three things: that is to wit, by a prompt and readye will: bycause indéede his will is to desire to profite in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176849:13"/> in the waye of Vertue.</p>
               <p>For, it is a greate instigation or quickning forewardes to Honestie, to haue a readye will to become honest. There is nothing harde vnto hym that hathe a willing minde: as also there is nothing more vneasie and harde, than one to be constrayned against his wil, or to drawe hym to a yéeldyng wyll. Therefore is the olde Prouerbe true: It is a foolishe thing, to leade Dogges to hunting againste their willes: that is to say, to enforce hym that is vnwilling and refuseth any kinde of study. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Comicall Poet <hi>Terence</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>nce.</note> sayde wel: There is nothing so easie, but may be hard, if it be done with an euill will. <hi>Lactantius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>antius.</note> in his first booke of Christiā Institutions doth say, that Vertue, &amp; not the Image of Vertue, is to be worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: and it is to be reuerenced, not with any Sacrifice or solempne prayer: but by onely fréewil, earnest purpose and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. After we once haue a will and loue to attaine Vertue, with two other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts is that willing minde to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propped
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176849:13"/> and safely fenced: that is to say wyth Patience and Abstinence: that it shoulde suffer the rather many thinges, and chiefly abstaine from fleshlye plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures.</p>
               <p>Hée that desireth Vertue, hath néede of much patience, that hée may the more quietly beare Aduersitie, Laboure and Trauaile: he shoulde suffer the better calamitie and miserie: and as <hi>Virgil</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> sayth in his sixt booke of <hi>Aeneidos:</hi> Let hym not giue place to euill: but on the other side, let him goe on his waye with more lustie courage. For, according to <hi>Valerian</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Valerian.</note> in his sixte booke: Vertue is wont to hate thē that be féeble minded: that is, Vertue hateth those that be of fearfull heartes, hauing in them no hold of stedfastnesse nor boldnesse at al. That both Patience and Abstinence, are néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to obtayne Vertue, <hi>Horace</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horace.</note> sheweth in these Verses. The childe that ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth to attaine vnto the marke that he wisheth for, shall suffer many things in his race, shall wearily passe on the brunte of laboure and sweate, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176849:14"/> shall be subiect to cold: yea, and hée must abstaine from Wine and Womē. More wisely also doeth that Christian Poet declare, that Patience is necessary to be ioyned to Vertue, saying: Strong Patience is a companiō of al Vertues, and intermingleth hir helpe amongest them all. There is no doubtfull battaile taken in hande withoute this Vertue: For, Vertue is a Widow, whiche Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot strengthen. Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse to brag: For, God bringeth downe euery proude thing: greate thinges perishe: thinges puffed vp with Pride, cracke in sunder: and they that swell through Loftinesse, are soone oppressed. Learne therefore to put awaye haughtie and proude lookes and loftie stomackes: Learne to take héede of the pitte before thy féete, howe loftie a fellowe soeuer thou be, and spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest no cruell threates. The common saying is of oure Mayster Christe, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching flourishing Force. The humble heartes doe clime to the Skie, and the proude Gluttons minde on the Duste doeth lye.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:176849:14"/>
                  <head>Of Abstinence.</head>
                  <p>MAnye learned men haue witnessed, that Abstinence from bodilye plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures is necessarye to obtayne Vertue. <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> in his newe booke of Rhetorike, sayeth: He that iudgeth a pleasaunte life to be best, suche a one can not leade hys life with Vertue. <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Valerius Maximus.</note> in his fourth booke sayeth, that the City whiche hathe ouermuche yéelded vnto pleasure, hath lost his greatest rule, and cannot defende libertie. But, the Citie that is delighted in Laboure and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise, kéepeth his gouernment, and is able to giue fréedome vnto others. <hi>Lactanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactātius.</note> in his sixte Booke, lefte a Writing, that there is a thréefolde degrée of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: The first degrée is, to abstaine from euill works: the second is, to refraine frō euill wordes: and the thirde is, to kéepe thy selfe from euill thoughts. That man whiche clymeth vp to the firste steppe or degrée, is noted iuste ynoughe: hée that mounteth vp to the second degrée, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is nowe perfect in him, so that he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offend in déede nor in word: and hée
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176849:15"/> that hath ascended vp to the third steppe or degrée, séemeth truly to haue gotten, euen the very Image of God: For, it is (in a maner) aboue the nature of man, not so much as to admit in thought, that whiche is euill to be done, or wicked to be spoken. Euery one therefore, that is willing to get Vertue, hath néed of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Abstinence. He hath néede of Patience, to the ende he may patientlye suffer Aduersitie and Trauaile, that hée maye abhorre Idlenesse, and embrace Labour and paines takyng. For, <hi>Hesio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hesiodus.</note> the Poet sayde, that GOD placed Vertue on highe vpon a Rocke, that we shoulde séeke for hir by manye doubtfull and hard sweates. Here vppon, the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers spent more Oile than Wine: they suffered very muche Trauell: they were very little or neuer Idle at all: for Idlenesse<note place="margin">Idlenesse.</note> weakeneth Vertue, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour strengthneth hir. Abstinence is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so néedefull, that we may abstaine from Vices. For Vertue is nothing else, than the flying from Vice, as <hi>Horace</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horace.</note> truelye witnesseth. The Minde béeing thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176849:15"/> and prepared wyth Patience and Abstinence: that is to say, willingly and with glad desire, wée muste searcho the Bookes and Writinges of learned men, what the meane and way is to get Vertue and Honestie. The Authoures of good Learning do affirme, and chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Laertius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Laertius.</note> in his booke of the liues of Philosophers, that all kinde of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hath néede of thrée things,<note place="margin">Three thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarye to Vertue.</note> that is to say, Nature, Instructiō, and Custom: whiche is, Wit, Knowledge and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise.</p>
                  <p>These things there are, which bée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite vnto Vertue: that is, a quicke &amp; a sharpe Wit: and not a clownish and dul Wit. <hi>Plato</hi> sayth, that a Wise man, whiche is once endued with Vertue, can not at all be perfect, vnlesse he doe excell others both in Wit and in Knowledge, and is also adorned with the partes of Prudence. All the Philosophers (euen as many as are read to haue bin in olde time) flourished in excellent and noble Wittes. Herevpon <hi>Lactantius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactantiu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> in his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde booke saide, that there were twoo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176849:16"/> degrées of Wisedome: the firste was, to vnderstande Falsehoode: and the second was, to knowe the Truth: and that all Vnderstanding and Knowledge, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth and commeth from a poolished and fine Witte.<note place="margin">VVitte.</note> The same <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his seconde booke sayth, that those whiche do allowe the deuises of Auncestors with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any iudgemēt, take away Wisdom from themselues, and are led awaye of others, like vnto brute beastes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Witte is necessary, bothe to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of Vertue, and to iudge also the instructions of other menne. In oure Wittes (saith <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> in hys Tusculane questions) are ingendred certain Séeds of Vertues: which, if they mighte haue libertie to growe vp: they (of their own nature) would bring vs to a blessed life. If certaine Séedes of Vertues bée en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed in oure Wittes: sure it is, that out of the same Wit (as out of a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surie) Vertues do growe and spring. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man by his owne Witte, doeth ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther séeke for Vertues: or else do muche better, sucke them vp, &amp; learne thē, from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176849:16"/> an Instructor or teacher: Therfore, the auncient Philosophers tooke none vnto them to bée instructed of them and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vnlesse they had first tryed and sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out their Wittes. Whiche, if they were founde dull or harde, then woulde they not take them to bée instructed of them. For <hi>Quintilian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quintiliā.</note> doth affirme, that Preceptes and Instructions, doe to him that hath no Witte, no more good, than tilling doeth the barraine fieldes, howe muche soeuer they bée still laboured and ploughed: which notwithstanding brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth neuer the more fruite. Yet all suche as haue but dull and fruitelesse Wittes, oughte not to dispaire, but to take vpon them for such a good purpose) the greater Laboure and Diligence: whereby, at length, the har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes of their Wittes maye be preuailed against and ouercome, as <hi>Quintilian</hi> witnesseth in his firste Booke, and the firste chapiter. One manne (indeede) doeth e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cell an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Witte: but yet so, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may be able to doe more or lesse: For, there is no man, whiche still getteth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176849:17"/> by hys Trauell and Diligence. For, althoughe it be not in euerye mans power to goe vnto <hi>Corinth,</hi> wée oughte not therefore to omitte to put in tryall what therein may be done: For, <hi>Horace</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horace.</note> sayeth: It is our partes to goe forthe a little although not far: that is, to make a meane or small Progresse. And Profit is to be commended, although by reason of the rudenesse of thy Wit, thou maist go no further.</p>
                  <p>Betwixte him that hath Witte, and him that hathe none, there is a double difference. First, he that hath Wit, doth of his own accorde (and that spéedily) fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after Vertue: euen like as an Horse that is swifte in his course, which is at pleasure to be kept backe with the bitte or bridle. But, as he that is rude witted, is like to an Horse that must be driuen forwardes to his race with the sharpnes of the Spurre: so the grosse and dul Wit is to be stirred vp and made sharpe with earnest Labour and Diligence. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, <hi>Quintillian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quintilian.</note> reporteth of <hi>Isocrates,</hi> who had two scholers, namely <hi>Ephorus</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:176849:17"/> and <hi>Theopompus:</hi> the one wittie, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che (he saide) had néede of Bridles: and the other a dullarde, which he sayd, had néede of Spurres. The second difference is, a noble Witte doth not long endure: or els, such things as before it did learn, it doth not kéepe in memorie: euen as those too timely Apples doe soone rotte. But, harde and rude Wits, more slow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do waxe tender, and yet continue far longer. By Laboure therefore, meane Wittes are made fitte for Vertue: For, <hi>Erasmus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Erasmu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> sayth: By Learning, the Wits of men do waxe softe and tender.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Learning, of Knowledge, and of Instruction.</head>
                  <p>NOw we haue some thing talked of the Wit, we haue néede also to saye somewhat of Art<note place="margin">Arte,</note> and of Instructiō: For Nature and Witte alone, are to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanded not sufficient, vnlesse that Instruction also come therevnto by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: which maketh that perfect, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was vnperfecte. Therefore sayeth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176849:18"/>
                     <hi>Cicero,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>o.</note> in his third Booke of newe Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torike, that Art doth ratifie and encrease the giftes of Nature. Again, in the same Rhethorike (the fourth Booke) <hi>Cicero</hi> affirmeth: That like as an vntamed Horse, althoughe he be well made, by nature cannot be fitte for those vses and commodities whiche are requyred of an Horse: so an vnlearned man, althoughe he be Wittie, yet he cannot attaine vnto Vertue: bycause withoute Learning, Vertue cannot be (of any) attained.</p>
                  <p>Herevpon (in times passed) were those heathen men moued to erect and buylde Schooles: firste, at <hi>Athens</hi> the moste flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing Citie then at that time in all the Country of <hi>Greece,</hi> and also in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that Youth in them might bée in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed, both touching Knowledge and good Maners.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ledge <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>od Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Which twoo, withoute Instruction are verye hardely procured and gotten. Therefore the Philosopher <hi>Aristippus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>pus.</note> did compare an ignoraunte and vnlearned man vnto a Stone. For, being in times paste asked of a certaine auntient Father, what it shoulde profite
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176849:18"/> his sonne to be instructed in Learning: made vnto him this answere: If nothing else (sayeth he) yet at the leaste he shall not sitte as one Stone vpon an other on the Scaffolde: hée shall not then be (as it were) a Stone amongst learned men. The verye Ethnickes did knowe, that Vertue was gotten by Instruction in Learning: who had Schoolemaisters at home with them, whiche shoulde learne their Chyldren in Artes and in Vertue: and which was a thing so greatlye reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious among the Athenians, that they made a lawe, that the children shoulde not be constrayned to nourishe or helpe their Parentes, when they be far stric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in yeres: vnlesse, in their youth they had of them bin committ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d vnto Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and Teachers to instructe them, &amp; therewith to be furnished with Vertue. To gette Vertue, wée haue néede of a double Instruction: one (as it were) a double Instruction, and the other a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner of Instructing. The Bookes that are read, do giue vnto the Dombe, Instruction: which (in their maner and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176849:19"/> kinde) doe teache without the sounde of any voyce. The other Instruction is, of liuing Maisters: who with the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sounde of the mouth, bringeth foorthe, and powreth into the eares of yong mē, the Rules and precepts of Vertue. The liuely Learning of the Mayster, is farre much better, than the senselesse or dumb knowledge of the Booke. Therefore cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine auntient Philosophers, are read, to haue measured or passed throughe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers lands and countries, neither lefte they anye that were not gone vnto. <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras, Empedocles, Democritus,</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> did sayle into strange Countries, to the obtayning and winning of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: and after they had ended the course of their peregrination, they surely found it. They were not contented with a sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowishe and lighte studie, whiche they might haue hadde at home within their owne walles: but they applyed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vnto other places, where they mighte knowe what shoulde beste be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them to learne: where they knew learned men: and not Bookes, but skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176849:19"/> Instructors and Teachers.</p>
                  <p>Nowe,<note place="margin">Foure Book<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> are chiefely<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> be envred, t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> the obtaynin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> of a good an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> godly life.</note> to saye something concerning Bookes: wée haue to vnderstande, that the Bookes of foure Authoures (among others) are chiefly to be red and envred: that is to say, of suche Poets as be wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of honest thinges, of Hystoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, of Philosophers, and aboue all, of the holye Scriptures. Good and honest Poets, do very much make and conduce a good and honest life: so that in old time, the most learned cities of the Grecians, woulde firste of all instructe their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Poetrie: thereby affirming, that Poets were onely Wise. In Poets, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are broughte vppe in Vertue: as <hi>Horace</hi> moste truelye sayde in hys E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle.</p>
                  <p>A Poet doeth fashion the tender and yong stutting mouth of a Child. Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately also after, he then frameth hys minde with right louely and friendelye preceptes: yea, he instructeth him wyth examples, and comforteth him also in al his pouertie and sicknesse. Secondly. the Bookes of Hystoriographers, whiche do
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176849:20"/> also propose and sette forth vnto vs, the actes of Noble menne, and their maners also and fortune. Out of whose commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable and worthy life of Praise, bothe the meane to liue well, is thereby got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: as also by the rashe temerositie and vnlucky chaunces of them, wée maye be made the more warie and circumspecte, and so take their Rashenesse for our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, whiche is very apt and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto vs. Therefore saith <hi>Diodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>orus.</note> It is good for vs to amend our liues, by the offences of others: and to be able also to know, what is to be desired, and what to be auoyded by the examples of other men. An Hystorie (sayth <hi>Beroal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>aldus.</note>) doeth muche inflame vs vnto that thing, which is good and honest: It ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth Vices: yea, it lifteth vp the good, and subiecteth much the wicked. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, The Philosophers Bookes, whiche hath giuen forth Preceptes of Vertue, are <hi>Aristotles</hi> ten Bookes of Ethickes: <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ro.</note> his tenth Booke also of Dueties: <hi>Lactantius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ntius.</note> of his Diuine Institution: as also <hi>Erasmus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>mus.</note> of Ordayning a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176849:20"/> Prince: and manye other Bookes, whiche haue described plainely the way to liue vprightly, and honestly. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (and aboue all) the Bookes of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures:<note place="margin">To confesse God, is our only vvised</note> by whome we are tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte to knowe GOD, and whome wee must also acknowledge to be the Maker of all things, and that he alone is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true Wisedom of men, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> affyrmeth in his seconde Booke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>That Pouertie is no let, vnto the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of Ʋertue.</head>
                  <p>THere is no cause why any estate or sorte of menne, shoulde accuse or finde faulte with Pouertie,<note place="margin">Pouertie.</note> as thought it were a plucker backe from Vertue: for Pouertie (as <hi>Apuleius</hi> witnesseth) was in times paste naturall among the Philosophers: Yea, and it is manifeste, that whosoeuer hath attained vnto any kind of Commendation or Praise, hath bin firste nourished vp from his Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, in the state of Pouertie. In time of the olde World, Pouertie was the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176849:21"/> vp of all Cities:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>se of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e.</note> the finder out of all Artes, without sinne and wickednesse: plentifull also in all kinds of Glorie: and among al Nations, it enioyed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and praise. These are the words of <hi>Apuleius.</hi> If any man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be oppressed with Pouertie, let him followe the Philosopher,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ntes.</note> who béeyng constrayned through Pouertie, didde in the night season draw water for mony, that he in the day time might haue foode and norishment, and whereby he might the better giue himselfe to Learning &amp; Study.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>nsaile.</note> Whilest we haue therfore time, let vs here take paines, that wée (by it) may deserue that which we must of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie liue vpon: and that we maye get Vertue, whiche commeth and offereth hirselfe vnto all that diligently laboure in their vocation and calling. Herevpō <hi>Seneca</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ca.</note> saide: Thou shalt finde Vertue in the Temple, in the Market place, in the Court, yea, and standing also by the walles of thine house, althoughe but of darke and duskie coloure, hauing to thy selfe knottie and harde handes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:176849:21"/> no other thing is signified, than that Vertue also loueth and embraceth suche menne, as are giuen to Laboure and to take paines.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Whether Vertue may be attained without Learning.</head>
                  <p>BVt, some man peraduenture will saye: There are manye vnlearned men, which neuer did learne letter, that be yet notwithstanding, truly counted &amp; iudged to be right honest mē. We must answere indéede, that many men of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Witte, are ofte led to Vertue without Learning: as <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth in his Booke of Orations, saying: I haue knowne many men of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent minde and Vertue (althoughe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede withoute Learning) hauing in a maner the Diuine habite of Nature it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, as of their own selues: and I haue also séene them to be very temperate, so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and graue. This also I muste ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioine to the praise and Vertue of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned: that is, that Nature is able to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176849:22"/> do muche more without Learning, than Learning withoute Nature. And this same therefore I vnite or knit togither, when a certaine fine speache, and stabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of Learning, shall come to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and notable Nature: than the whiche, I know not what a more noble &amp; rare thing is wonte to remaine. These are the wordes of <hi>Cicero.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Exercise.</head>
                  <p>BEside Witte and Knowlege in the thirde place: wée muste vse Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Exercise. Otherwise let no manne bestow his labour and study to get Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. For, as <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> recordeth in his third Booke of newe Rhetorike: In euerye kinde of Discipline, the Rules and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Arts are but weake and of smal force: vnlesse they be exercised wyth continuall diligence, and with very long vse and custome. And also in good memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Learning but smally auaileth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse it be perfected, and so allowed by Painfulnesse, by Labor and Diligence. And <hi>Lactantius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactantius.</note> in hys thirde Booke, saith: That Artes are learned, not that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176849:22"/> they maye be onely knowne, but that they maye also bée putte in exercise. And they are practised, eyther in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of mannes life, eyther else for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, or for praise and glorie. <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> left a writing in his Offices, that all Praise and Vertue did consiste, not in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but in Practise: that is to saye, It is but a small thing to know what Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue is, what Honestie is, and what Vice is, vnlesse we also exercise, and put Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in practise.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The exercising of our Knowlege, for the obtayning of Vertue.</head>
                  <p>OVt of these saide foure Bookes: that is to wit, out of Poets, oute of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiographers, Philosophers, and the holy Scriptures, if wée desire the fruite and profit of true Vertue and Honestie, it behoueth vs to folowe the custome of Bées in gathering of Hony. For, Bées<note place="margin">Bees,</note> that doe gather Hony, do flye about here and there among dyuers flowers, taste also of many floures, and sucke vp also the iuyce of many flowers. Then they also carry with them into their Hyues
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176849:23"/> some swéete moysture of their diligente and painefull Trauell: whiche they also lay downe and presse it togither, and therof commeth the Hony. And by thus often doing, they heape togither at lēgth good quantitie of Hony, which is a swéet rewarde of their laboures. No otherwise oughte he to doe (whosoeuer he be) that is desirous and studious of Learning &amp; Vertue, and that otherwhyles do séeke to become a man: wherevnto, he muste haue foure manner of Exercises. The first Exercise is,<note place="margin">Foure Exercises. The firste Exercise.</note> that out of those things whiche he either heareth or readeth, hée doe gather oute into a noting Table, those things, whiche shall be profitable to Eloquence and Vertue, as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Storehouse of Memorie, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he shal at any time reade, that may further Eloquence or Vertue. For, eche of them requireth a notable manner, as <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> witnesseth in his fourth Booke of his olde Rhetorike, saying thus: Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome withoute Eloquence is but a smal profite vnto a Citie or Cities: and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence withoute Wisedome, did for the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176849:23"/> moste parte hurte, and neuer profited at all. Therefore shal euery Student haue two Noting Bookes, into the which, he may gather such things, as he both hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth &amp; readeth. Into the one, that which teacheth Eloquence: and into the other, that, which teacheth Vertue: euen lyke vnto a Couetous man gathering trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, who hathe diuers Chestes, into the whiche he putteth his Siluer by it selfe, and the Golde by it selfe. This Exercise didde <hi>Plinie</hi> the Writer of the naturall Historie, vse: of whom, <hi>Plinie</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plinie.</note> the second (his Vncle) writeth in his Epistles, that he read nothyng, whyche hée didde not also picke out after he read it.</p>
                  <p>The second Exercise<note place="margin">The secō Exercised</note> is, that he must shut vp in his memorie, those thinges whiche he gathered oute: and thinke, that sometime he may haue néede to vse them: as <hi>Macrobius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Macrobius</note> witnesseth in hys sixte booke Saturnall, saying: That this is the beste waye into reading and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, to followe those things which thou allowest in others: and suche things as thou doest most of all wonder at in other
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176849:24"/> mens sayings, to tourne them to thine own behoofe and purpose. Which thing, the Latines did among themselues: and also notable men among the Gréekes, were wont so to doe. These out of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crobius.</hi> This is not now simply to hear an Authour, to learne onely his words, or to vnderstande his Orations: but out of his writings to gather vnto hymselfe Eloquence, and the way also to liue wel, like as meate, onely put into the mouth and chawes, doth not profite the bodye, except it go downe into the Stomacke, and there be concocted, and so at length is turned into bloude and flesh: So nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reading nor hearing anye thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth, vnlesse it be tourned to the vse of Speaking, and that rather speaking discréetely and wisely.</p>
                  <p>The thirde Exercise<note place="margin">The thirde Exercise.</note> is this, that no day doe passe away withoute some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, after the example of the cunning Paynter <hi>Apelles:</hi> who daylye was so well occupyed, that at the least, he pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or drewe out some little line. After this custome and order, the gréedie guts
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176849:24"/> also of the worlde, doe vse to lay aside e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day, some péece of Coyne into their treasurie, for the encrease of their after store. For, smal things oftetimes, put to small things, at length are made many things: as <hi>Hesiodus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hesiodus.</note> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Poet witnesseth: If thou assayest to adde trifles to trifles, and doest it often: in the ende, a greate heape is gathered togither.</p>
                  <p>In this Exercise, we must not labour to learne muche, as it were but for one day, but we must with Diligence learn it perfectly and well. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>refore answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Apelles</hi> a certaine vnskilfull Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that bragged of his spéedie dispatch in Painting of an Image: I wonder not (sayth hée) at that: for manye more such fonde pictures, mayste thou soone painte and dispatche. Wherefore, this saying of <hi>Cato</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cato.</note> is to be folowed: Soone ynough, if it be well done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Augustus Caesar</note> had thereof this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe: Make haste slowly: that is to say, Make slowe hast on thy worke, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by meaning, to do it warily and wittily, and not too too hastily: For, somewhat
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176849:25"/> flowe and prouident going forewardes, doth muche more profite, than post hast without Arte or Reason.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The fourth and laste Exercise.</note>Now, the last and fourth Exercise is, that thou repeate in the Euening, such thinges, as thou haste bothe hearde and read on the day time. Which vse and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom, <hi>Cato</hi> did kéep, as <hi>Philelphus</hi> saith in his seconde Booke <hi>Of the Education of Children.</hi> And <hi>Apuleius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apuleius.</note> writeth of certaine in <hi>India,</hi> which are called Bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophisters: who neyther knewe howe to tylle the grounde, howe to plowe the fieldes, neither howe to tame Horses, nor howe to yoke Oxen, ne yet howe to sheare Shéepe. Yet, both the aged Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters &amp; the yonger Schollers, had Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom then wonderfully in reuerence: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing nothing so muche, as Drowsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and Idlenesse of the mind.</p>
                  <p>After that the Table was once coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, before Meate was set thereon, all the yongmen out of diuers places (as the manner there was) came togyther to eate. Then the Maisters asked thē what good they had done from the dawning of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176849:25"/> the Day, vntill that present time. Then one called to minde, and answered, that he (among certaine which were at Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde) had made Peace and Concorde. An other sayde, that he did obey his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, whiche commaunded hym to doe a certayne thing: An other saide, that throughe musing by himselfe, he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised somewhat: And an other said, that he had learned somewhat. But he that coulde not bring or say something, was thrust forth out of the Doores to his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and businesse, and so went without his supper. These are the wordes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puleius.</hi> So also shoulde euerye manne that is studious of Vertue, folowe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by hymselfe in the Euening) the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Shéepe, whiche being in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning broughte from their Pastures, doe then chew their Cudde in their Coates: that is, do eate againe and teare with their téeth the same Fodder, which they before had cropped vpon the day time: and do also giue Milke to their Shéepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearde through the same Fodder, which in the day tyme they had plucked vp. So
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176849:26"/> in like maner, he that loueth and studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Vertue, oughte in the Euening to repeate those thinges, whiche hée before read or hearde: as well those that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vnto Eloquence, as vnto Vertue.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, let hym tourne them vnto Milke: that is, let him vse them to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and honest behoofe of his life: and let him shewe forth that thing, wherein he hathe bin also profitable vnto others: like as the Shéepe being yet filled with Milke, doe shewe forthe themselues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Shéepehearde, that they in the day time haue eaten and chewed grasse: and that they haue not spent the daye in Idlenesse. This also will profite, yea, &amp; that not a little, to stande in contention with another whether he hath more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited in Eloquence or Vertue. For, then doeth euerye manne proue howe muche he doth eyther know or not know, when as he hath entred into comparison with an other. Therefore writeth <hi>Suetonius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Suetonius.</note> in his Booke of noble Grammarians, that in times passed (in the schooles) this was the vse and custome, that the Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176849:26"/> before dinner shoulde dispute togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But after dinner (their Bookes layde aside) they shoulde then declame, or fall into reasoning and arguing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>VVhat comelinesse, and vvhat Vertue and Honesty is by Man to bee kepte in euery time and age. CHAP. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He life truely in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> trade of Vertue and Honesty, consisteth in twoo thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that is to saye, in the séemely adorning of Man hymselfe, and in honest dealing also towardes others: as <hi>Macrobius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Macrobius</note> witnesseth in his first Booke and first chapter of <hi>Scipio</hi> his Dreame, saying, that by Vertue a good man was firste made Gouernor of hymselfe: then, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fter that, of the common wealth. And it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176849:27"/> is méete indéede, that a good man do first gouerne and instructe himselfe, before he be a Gouernor or Instructor of others, Herevpon was <hi>Thales</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thales.</note> the Philosopher demaunded, who was a King indéede, who answered: He that is taughte to rule hymselfe. Dwell at home with thy selfe, that thou mayest knowe of what abilitie thou arte. But howe he oughte to gouerne and instruct himselfe by Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, he must most diligently learne: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he may here know by these Precepts following.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>He that wil teach and rule himselfe honestly, muste keepe these sixe precepts folowing.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Silence.</note>THe firste Precept is, that he learne to be silent, and to holde his peace: &amp; that he loue Silente more than muche babbling: For Silence sheweth foorthe a Wise man: but vaine and much bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, argueth a foolishe man, who cannot refraine to holde his peace. By Silence
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176849:27"/> doeth a Philosopher no lesse vtter his Wisedome, than he doth by open spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: as <hi>Macrobius</hi> witnesseth in hys seauenth Booke and first chapter: that is to say, It is no lesse token or signe of Wisedom, a man to hold his peace, thā otherwise to speake. Herevppon, as saith <hi>Apuleius,</hi> was <hi>Pythagoras</hi> firste called a Philosopher, bycause he taughte his Disciples firste of all to be Silent and holde their peace. And the first Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that Scholler whiche should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Wise, was, to refraine his tong, and to kéep his words within the walles and compasse of his téeth. <hi>Socrates</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Socrates.</note> also being asked of a certaine man, howe a man mighte be made Wise: did gyue vnto hym two preceptes: Firste, that he shoulde more often holde his peace, than vtter speache: The other precepte was, that he shoulde learne to speake.</p>
                  <p>It is euident by thrée signes,<note place="margin">It is bette<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> to holde our peace than to speake.</note> that it is better for a man to holde his peace, than to speake. First, by Nature, which hath bestowed vppon Man, but one Mouth and two Eares: to the ende we shoulde
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176849:28"/> speake lesse than we heare. Secondely, by the custome of the antient Romanes, who were wont to Painte <hi>Angerona,</hi> their Goddesse of Silence, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hir mouth sealed vp with Waxe. And the Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Painted their God of Silence, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> stopping his mouth wyth hys twoo fyngers. Thirdelye, by the doctrine of ancient Philosophers who neuer condemned any thing more in Man, than much Talke, saying, that therefore Nature had giuen vnto Man Téeth and Lippes before his Tongue, bycause they mighte kéepe it vnder, and that it shoulde not be ouer-much a bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or busie speaker. Therefore <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Xenocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>es.</note> being demaunded of his Silence, aunswered: that it neuer repented hym in kéepyng of Silence: but that he ofte repented him for his much speaking. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, lette hym before learne to speake those thinges, whiche beste becommeth him to speake: but no lies or forged thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: for he that is bolde to speake fained and hidden thinges, is to be noted but blacke coloured, as <hi>Horace</hi> recordeth:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176849:28"/> neyther yet those wordes, whiche (as <hi>Plinie</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plinie.</note> sayth) shall returne by the throat: that is to saye, hurtefull to the speaker: neyther backbiting words, whereby an other mans estimation and honor is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praued or euill spoken of: no, neyther yet secreate words, eyther words spoken in Drinke: but only those things, whyche are good and honest, chaste also, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and true. And it followeth: He that truely worshippeth Vertue, muste also kéepe all other things in secreate. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore sayd <hi>Ouid:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> It is a notable Vertue to kéepe Silence: and on the other side, it is a grieuous faulte to speake suche things as are to be kepte close.</p>
                  <p>In Speaking therefore, this Lawe is to kepte: that is, when we are aboute to speake, thē to note, whether the thing whiche we woulde speake, be comely for the place, as also for the time: and likewise, whether it be apte vnto others purposes, then being there present. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we oughte also to speake, when Silence shall be eyther hurtefull vnto our selues, or vnto others. Thirdly, hée
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176849:29"/> ought to take good héede that he do not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuch busie himself in any matter at al: that is, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he kéepe measure in all such things as he mindeth to take in hād: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he doe ouerfarre deale in such things as be euil: nor yet ouersparingly to with holde from speaking or dooyng that, which is conuenient, good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>Terence</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Terence.</note> in <hi>Andria,</hi> (the first sceane) sayth in this maner: I thinke that to be profitable in the life of Man, where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ouermuche is done: that is, that Measure (by all meanes) be alwayes obserued and kepte. And herevppon the Learned haue said: that Vertue stil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted in the mean. And as <hi>Horace</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horace.</note> saith: There is a Measure in things: and there are also certaine limites thereof: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the compasse whereof, nothing that is Iuste can stande.</p>
                  <p>Vertue consisteth in the Meane: and Vice in excesse. Wherefore, in all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Meane and Measure is to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: and Excesse to the contrary, to be discommended. Therevpon, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et <hi>Hesiodus</hi> sayde: The Halfe is more
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176849:29"/> than the Whole: that is, that Mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is more to be commended in things, than Ouer-muche or no meane: for the common Prouerbe is: Euery thing that is too muche, is tourned into Vice, or to be noted in the worste parte. <hi>Cleobulus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cleobulus.</note>
                     <hi>Lindius,</hi> one of the <hi>.7.</hi> Sages of <hi>Greece,</hi> vsed to say: In euery thing, Measure is best. Fourthly, let him shun and auoide that thing, whiche he reproueth in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. By the testimony of <hi>Diogenes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Diogenes.</note> the Philosopher it is thus sayd: If thou wilt be a good man (as one endued with Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue) putte that away from thée, whyche thou despisest in another. And <hi>Cicero</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so saith: He that is ready to finde faulte with an other, oughte firste to be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse himself: for we can easily and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sée other mens faults: but as for our owne, wée hyde them and knowe them not. If euery man shoulde descende into his own selfe, &amp; so weygh wyth himselfe what maner a mā indéede he is, and also of what corrupted mind: truly he would then ceasse to taunt or nippe others: and so would first of all purge himselfe from
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:176849:30"/> Vices, and garnishe himselfe with Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Therefore, oure Sauiour Iesus Christ in his holy Gospell, beyng about to exhorte vs vnto Vertue, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that firste we shoulde caste oute the Beame from our own eies, and then the Moate from an other mannes eyes. We shoulde firste cure and heale oure selues, and after that, others. Fiftelye, let him learne to sustaine and suffer, as well Aduersitie as Prosperitie. Let him not ouermuche reioice, when Fortune fauoureth him: leaste the same Fortune being sodainly againe altered, he should then be ouermuche disquieted and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull. Neither in Aduersitie shoulde he ouermuche lament, after the example of <hi>Socrates:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ocrates.</note> who in eyther sorts of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune (which soeuer) is read to be alwais of like countenaunce and minde. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Plato</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>lato.</note> also being demaunded by what meanes a man shoulde be knowne to be wise, answeared: A Wise manne, when he is reprooued, is not therfore an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie or teastie, neither is he puffed vppe, when he is commended and praised.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:176849:30"/>
                  <p>For Vertue hath no acquaintance with Pride, bycause it is a very hatefull and euill Vice: neyther doeth it euer admit anye Desperation or Wrath: bicause they be also very hurtefull and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Vices. Wherefore, the common Prouerb is, that the man which is féeble and weake harted in Aduersitie, is not vnaptly compared to a Rushe. In eche fortune therefore, (both Aduersitie and Prosperitie) the custome of a certaine Philosopher is to be followed: who in Prosperitie was pensiue and sad (foresée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that after mirth, commonlye follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth sorrowe) and in Aduersitie was glad and mery, knowing by good expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that after the fall of euill, soone riseth vp goodnesse againe: for Fortune is very slipprie &amp; changeable. Therfore, in Prosperitie, let vs thinke that Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie will also followe: For, <hi>Plautus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plautus.</note> witnesseth in <hi>Amphitrio,</hi> that GOD doth so think it good and conuenient, that Sorrowe (as a companion) shoulde still followe after Delight and Pleasure. In Aduersitie therfore, let vs so thinke, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176849:31"/> God will make an ende of suche things, according to that saying of <hi>Virgil:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> And it will do a man good to remember these euilles, as felte in times paste. Sixtely, and lastly, let hym séeke means, to please bothe God and Wisemen: whiche, them to please, is doubtlesse the gretest praise and Vertue. For, he that seketh to please them, muste be of necessitie either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently good, or else at the leaste (in time) be of them made good. For, those whych be good, do onely loue suche as are good: and to the contrarie, the euill are louers of the euill. It is euident out of <hi>Seneca,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> that he, whyche wisheth for Vertue, oughte to take paines to please good mē: saying, Some good man is to be chosen vnto vs, and alwaies to be set before our eies: and that we may so liue, as though he euer looked vpon vs, and didde sée our doings in all things. For, he shall easily loue both vertuously and well, whiche is conuersant among good men, and which also liueth according to their good wils &amp; discriptions: and that none otherwise truly, than is the maner of women: who
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176849:31"/> attyring themselues before the Glasse, at length (when they are moste finelye adorned and decked) doe then come forth to shewe themselues.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of the maners and Vertues, of sundry times and Ages.</head>
                     <p>ALthoughe Honestie and Vertue doe very well beséeme and sette forthe a man: yet in dyuers times and ages, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and sundrye manners are requyred concerning Honestie. For, the Prouerb is: An other life, requyreth an other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of dyet, as also of other maners. For, the same thing doeth not conduce or so aptely profite in euery age: but as some things do become Childehoode, so other thinges doe belong vnto Youth, other things vnto the state of yong men, and other things also vnto mans state, and vnto olde men. For, in time of age, mens manners are ofte altered, and Nature likewise is soone chaunged.<note place="margin">The age of Māki<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> And vnto Mankinde, there is belonging sixe ages:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176849:32"/> that is to wit, the time of Infancie, the time of Childhood, the time of Youth, the state of Yongmen, Mans state, and Old age: Whereof euery one hathe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per office, Manners, and Qualities, as immediately followeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of Infancie.</head>
                     <p>THe first age of Mankinde after hys birth, is called Infancie: And it is so called, bycause it hathe not the vse of Speache. And no Maners or Vertues are to be prescribed vnto it, bycause it is not as yet capable of Reason: for it hath in it, neyther the vse of the Tongue, nor yet of Vnderstanding. Therefore, it oughte, by the onely Instruction of the Mothers or Nursses, to be here trained vp to suche purpose, and that it may liue in thys Worlde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:176849:32"/>
                     <head>Of Childhoode.</head>
                     <p>CHildhoode is the second age of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: namely, when Children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to speake: and not hauing as yet the full vse of Reason. They beare the name of Children, of this worde, <hi>Bua:</hi> that is, Childes Drinke, whyche they call <hi>Bua:</hi> béeing as yet vnable (and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Prudence, Reason, or Vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) to vtter forth their firste wordes. These (of this age) are timely to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed of their Parentes and Nursses: whereby, they maye begin the more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly to liue, in these sortes of manners following: that is to wit, that they tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know God: that they also do worship him in harte, and likewise in feruent prayers: as <hi>Hermannus Buschius</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hermānus Buschius.</note> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selleth in his Verse, where he exhorteth Children vnto Vertue. Let them (sayth he) obey theyr Parentes, and reuerence their Elders: let them be barred from too muche play, and also from euill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, least they be stained with noisome
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:176849:33"/> vices, before they firste begunne the vse of Reason: than the which, nothing may be more detestable, as <hi>Apuleius</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Apuleius.</note> doeth witnesse, saying: Who will not hate that Childe, which like a Monster sooner groweth vp strong in Wickednes, than in age, and is readye to hurte wyth myschiefe, or before he be of any bodilye stature, eyther to be but yong in yeres, and yet olde in Vice and Naughtinesse. Perfecte Prudence cannot as yet be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired or had in a Childe: whereas chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dishnesse it selfe doth still beare sway in hym: and in whom also the weakenesse of a very gréene or newe minde doe yet beare rule. Therefore, the Shippe play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and he rideth vpō a long Réede. For that cause, he ought not ouermuch to bée borne with all: leaste he be inclined and beate vnto Vices, and so alwayes after remaine wounded therewith: for that whiche in Youth hathe once sticked to the fleshe, will verye hardely in Age de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte from the bone. Wherefore, they are to be diligently instructed in these Preceptes, as <hi>Philelphus</hi> prescribeth in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:176849:33"/> his eighte Booke <hi>Of the Education of Children:</hi> that is to say, that they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe GOD (as is before noted) and be obedient both in words, in maners, and in the order of their body: and to goe also cleanly apparelled.<note place="margin">VVhat is to be auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> They maye not bée giuen vnto many wordes, neyther bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come lyars, nor be like vnto Beastes, or euill conditioned, neyther yet slowe in bodye, as are Asses: nor vncleane as Swine in the myre: eyther their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes vnbrushed, as Beggars: or fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie as stinking Goats: neyther vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a Stone, or as an <hi>Archadiā</hi> Asse. And after they be seauen yeares olde, let them be put vnto Schoolemaisters: for such was the maner of the Gentiles, as witnesseth <hi>Philelphus</hi> in hys seconde Booke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of Youth.</head>
                     <p>YOuth is, that Age, whiche is nexte vnto Childehoode, althoughe (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Perotus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Perotus.</note>) the Lawyers do putte
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:176849:34"/> and accounte Youth after young mans state: but by vse it is set before. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now, if they cā perfectly speake, they are (as therevnto fitte) to be commended vnto Schoolemaisters. And it is called Youth (as sayth <hi>Perotus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Perotus.</note>) of Helping: bycause it is then of strength, and apte to helpe his Parentes. For, it is then of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to dispatche businesse committed vnto it: and is also able to endure and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide Labour and Trauell. In this age, tender bringing vp is to be auoyded, as <hi>Quintilian</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Quintilian.</note> sayth in his firste Booke and thirde Chapiter:<note place="margin">Delicate bringing vppe of Youth, the inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> forasmuch, as Delicate bringing vp (sayeth he) corrupteth and weakeneth both the strength of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, and also of the Witte. What then will the elder Youth doe whiche hathe crepte vp in Purple? And they whiche are nowe daintily fedde in this Age, are also desirous of Dainties all their liues after. Whyche if they cannot obtayne: they yet labour wyth desire (as muche as they maye) bothe by righte and by wrong, to satisfie their daintie mouths. And so at lēgth fal to Loytring and Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:176849:34"/> to play, to Theft &amp; Robberie, &amp; to all kinds of Mischiefe. In this Age,<note place="margin">The maner of children in old time among the Romanes.</note> the Children of <hi>Rome</hi> did brag of the Gates of the Temple, of the Chaines whyche they had worne about their necke frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time of their Infancie (as it wer in tokē of renoūcing Childhood:) &amp; afterwards, being desirous to putte from them their Childishe manners, were clothed in a white Gown, Embrodered &amp; wroughte before with Purple, in token of a more pure, of a better, and more Honest lyfe: that beholding the whitenesse of the Gowne, they mighte flye from Vices, which make men blacke, foule, and hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto others: séeyng vppon them the brightnesse of the Purple, they mighte the rather thinke and endeuour therein themselues, that their liues shoulde so clearely shine, as might of all menne be commended and praised.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Dueties of Yong men.</head>
                  <p>FIrste of all, God is to worshipped, both with Prayer, and also with a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:176849:35"/> cleane hearte: then their Parentes, and next their Maisters. To obey those thrée, and also to shunne those thinges whiche letteth the accomplishemente of that whiche they doe commaunde: Lette them here learn, séeke, and daily execute the holy commaundementes of God. It is most plaine and manifest, that a yong man shoulde obey these thrée: for vpon them doth depēd our whole life.<note place="margin">VVhat Mā hath of God, of his Parents, &amp; of hys Maister.</note> Of God we haue our Soules: of oure Parentes we haue our Bodies: and of oure May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, we haue the Instruction of oure Soules. By the whiche oure life diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from brutishe or sauage Beastes. Therefore, that wée maye be thankefull vnto them: wée muste of righte loue and obey them.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of Yong mans estate.</head>
                     <p>THe state of a Young manne, is the fourth age: whiche beginneth wyth him at the yeares of <hi>.14.</hi> It is called the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:176849:35"/> State of a Young manne, or Young mans State, of thys Verbe <hi>Adolesco:</hi> whyche signifieth, to growe vp. For, at that time, menne do growe vppe in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in Strength, and in Reason, yea, in Vice also and in Vertue: although more inclined vnto Vice than vnto Vertue. And at that time, is euery mans nature and disposition first known, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto it is moste bente and affected. For before, thoroughe the small discretion of their age, it coulde not so well be known and discerned. For,<note place="margin">Terence in Andria.</note> (saieth <hi>Terence</hi>) so soone as they be Yong menne, they gyue themselues to some solace and pastime, as also vnto Study: eyther else to bring vp Horses, or Dogges to hunt withall: eyther to make much of Philosophie and of Learning. Vnto whome also <hi>Horace</hi> doeth agrée, in his Arte of Poetrie: <hi>A Yong man hauing no bearde,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in Youth.</note>
                        <hi>after hee hathe once gotten hys necke from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Yoke of hys Gouernour, gyueth hymselfe immediatelye vnto Ryding, to Hunting, and to solacing of hymselfe abroade, counting then Simplicitie to be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:176849:36"/> but Wickednesse: contemptuous also of all suche as gyue vnto hym good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: nothing regarding his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: very wastefull of his money: ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loftie, greedy, swifte also and readye to forsake suche thinges as oughte of hym to be beloued.</hi> This Age, that is to wit, Young mans State, is of twoo sortes: The one, from fouretéene to eyghtéene yeares doe continue, and is called, Yong mans State (béeyng without Bearde) bycause in those yeares Yongmen are wythout any Bearde: like as in times paste, <hi>Phoebus,</hi> that is, <hi>Apollo,</hi> stoode in the Temple of the Ethnickes withoute a Bearde, as sayeth <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> in his firste Booke <hi>Of Despised Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> touching <hi>Dionisius</hi> the Syracusian Tyrante: And at eightéene yeares, is the firste beginning that a Bearde doth growe: and men are then sayde to goe oute of the Beardelesse time, and so to stretche forwards vnto Mannes State. Into euery kinde of Wickednesse, doeth this Age caste a Yongman down head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long: as into Slouth and Idlenesse, into
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:176849:36"/> Pastimes and Playes, into Disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Surffetting, Ryot, haunting of Whoores, Pryde, and wastefull Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending: they vainelye consume theyr Substaunce: béeyng nothyng at all carefull for the life that shall followe: as all Comedies doe witnesse: whyche speake nothing else of Yong men, than, that they doe consume theyr riches vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Whoores, vpon Ryot, and Banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Hovv Yong men are to be trained vp of their Parents and Maisters, to Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp; Honestie.</head>
                     <p>WHereas (therefore) this Age aboue all others, is moste readye to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and doth daily more and more giue it selfe therevnto: and by reason of the lust of Youth, euen like vnto the yonger Colts, whom Youth doeth much pricke and moue forwardes. Therefore are Young menne to bée timely brideled:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176849:37"/> eyther of their Parentes, or else of theyr Maysters: and that none otherwise than are vntamed Horses to be tamed and broken of the Ryder wyth the touche of sharpe Spurres. By foure rules, the Parents or Maisters ought to bring vp their Youth to fruitfulnesse: That is to saye, by Instruction, by Warning, by Promise, &amp; lastly, by Praise and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How Instruction consisteth in sixe Preceptes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> FIrst Yong men ought to know, that God is chiefly and aboue all things to be worshippped &amp; reuerenced: who hathe created, who also féedeth &amp; preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth al things: &amp; who leaueth no sinne or any euill vnpunished, nor no good thing vnrewarded, giuing vnto the good an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall reward, and vnto the wicked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting punishement. And withoute whose grace and fauoure wée menne
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:176849:37"/> cannot do any thing, no, not liue one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of time. We ought therfore to take good héede, that we offend him not wyth an euil life. Secondly, that we maye not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> trust in any earthly riches: and chiefely, not to the beautie of the bodie. For the shape of the body, or the beautie therof, (whiche we counte good) is but a fading or brickle thing: &amp; therfore <hi>Virgil</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> said, <hi>Eglog. <hi>2. O faire childe, trust not to much vnto thy beautie: for white flourishing blossomes do soone fade awaye, and are by and by of none accompte.</hi>
                     </hi> Neyther let them ouermuch lament, if they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in bodye: but let them rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that they maye in their mindes be louely and faire: for, as <hi>Franciscus Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarcha</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Franciscus Petrarcha.</note> sayth in his booke of Aduersitie: It is better to bée made faire in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and in vertue, than to be borne fair in bodie. In this precepte, did <hi>Socrates</hi> oft instruct his scholers, commaundyng them to loke vpon the glasse: that, if they sawe themselues deformed in body: they should therefore labour to be made faire in minde: for the bodie is defiled, whyche
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:176849:38"/> kéepeth a foule soule in it: euen like as a beautifull Tombe, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kepeth therein a rotten and stincking carkasse. Therfore doth Christ in his Gospell call the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riscis,<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> painted Sepuchres: bycause they appeared to be religious and good: but yet were inwardly rauening Woolues. <hi>Socrates</hi> gaue commaundement, that if any were blemished in body, they should then séeke for the beautie of the minde, by Knowledge and Vertue: which shold be more noble and longer to endure, thē <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> any corporal beautie in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they put not their trust in riches, in worldly goods, nor in money: but in only Knowledge and Vertue: trusting, that they shal then become rich and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie. For, to be learned and wise, is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in déede to be riche. As for common &amp; worldly riches, they perish most wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; come to nought. For, in times past, many there were, which were most rich &amp; wealthy: but sooner than a word could be spoken, they were made most poore &amp; beggerly: as it is read of <hi>Croesus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>roesus.</note> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most wealthy King of <hi>Lydia.</hi> Riches are not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:176849:38"/> woorthy so to be beloued, as though they were in déede precious goods: for <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> in his fourth booke of newe Rethoricke alledgeth, saying: If thou wilt compare Riches with Vertue, they shal scarselye be worthye to be the handmaidens and seruants of Vertue. Therfore, yong mē (whilest their wits and age do flourish) let them get vnto them some wayfaring man vntil old age: that is to say, Vertue &amp; Knowledge: for, they by it, in old age haue gotten both honor, safetie, prayse, &amp; true Vertue. Wherfore <hi>Thales</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Thales.</note> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher being on a time demaunded what yong mē ought to lerne: answered saying: Those things which they shold vse in their old age: &amp; y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> shewing forth of Vertue &amp; Knowledge. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whatsoeuer they sée to be hurtful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> others, or y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> of others are to be auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same thing let thē also shun: let thē begin to be wise by other mēs harmes: &amp; so let thē instruct thēselues, &amp; reform bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their liues. The vices which do cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt &amp; disprofit others, be these: namely, Disobedience, lying, much babling, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:176849:39"/> wickednesse,<note place="margin">Vices, to be auoyded of children.</note> playing for mony, whorehūting, drūkēnesse, wastful &amp; vain spending of goods loytring and idlenesse, and haunting of naughtie companye.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, let the examples both of good &amp; naughtie men be set before them: and let the liues and ends of them, be truely told vnto them: and how that the euill wyth euil were rewarded: as also to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, the good with good. Herevppon, the auntient yong men of Rome, in the beginning or prime time of their yong age, did clothe themselues with a mans gowne, that they might by little &amp; little beginne and stretch forwardes towards such a life, as is worthy the praise of an honest man. Then were they broughte forth to the common market place, that they might there know and sée the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon life of man to be of two sorts: that is,<note place="margin">The Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>uous and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>he vicious <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>fe, hovve <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>iuerselie <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>hey are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>varded.</note> a life vitious and vertuous. The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious life, hath alwayes an euil end: but the good and vertuous life, being (at the first) but hard and thorny, is afterwards rewarded with goodnesse, and that for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer &amp; euer. Therfore, <hi>Hercules,</hi> in times
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176849:39"/> past (being a yong man) did rather choose to serue vertue with paines taking (kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that after such labour there shuld folowe a reward) than to Seruice wyth loytring and idlenesse: as <hi>Cicero</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of him in his first booke of <hi>Offices.</hi> Sixtely, let them be exercised in labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and ernest businesse: let them in no wise be suffered to giue themselues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to idlenesse, lest they fall into filthy luste and desire. For, <hi>Ouid</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> sayth, <hi>If you once take away idlenesse, the bowe of luste is soone broken.</hi> And therefore did the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Romaines exercise their childrē in martial affairs, in warring, in fighting, &amp; in swimming. Yong men therfore are to be exercised with continuall labour &amp; trauel, after the manner of horsekepers, who dayly do bring forth out of the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles from stréete to stréete, into the field, rough and vntamed horses, that by run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and coursing of them, they might the rather accustome them to the vse of spurres and bridles: and not suffer them to rotte or vainly weare away through Idlenesse or want of exercise.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:176849:40"/>
                     <head>Of Warning.</head>
                     <p>NOw, secondly, (besides the order of instruction giuen vnto yong men,) parents and masters ought to admonish them of their errours. For, if they haue erred in any thing: they ought then to be taught what should be better and more honest for them to do. Let your accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med talke in theyr presence be good and honest: that by such continuall warning, they may be made the more vertuous &amp; honest. For, words be of force to moue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> minde: and that which of man is moste commenlye hearde, that is most surely fixed and kept in his heart. Let them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so herein be admonished: that is, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they orderly followe the steps of their honest parents and kinsefolke: for, so <hi>Aeneas</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Aeneas.</note> in the .12. <hi>Aeneid,</hi> exhorteth &amp; warneth his son <hi>Ascanius</hi> to learn Vertue of him his Father, saying vnto him: <hi>My son, learn of me, the waye of Vertue and true La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: but touching Fortune, learne that of others. My right hand shal be thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence from al assaults, and that shall sette
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:176849:40"/> thee among many great rewards. Se that thou in such wise do remember me, whē thou shalt once attaine vnto the yeers &amp; state of a man.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of Promise.</head>
                     <p>THirdly, let it be also promised vnto them, that they shal receiue (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse) great rewards, both here of vs and else where, if they shal once embrace and follow Vertue: as <hi>Horace</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Horace.</note> sayeth in his Epistles: <hi>Thou good felow, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther soeuer Vertue shal leade or guyde thee, thyther most happilye goe on thy way, and doubtlesse, for thy desarts, thou shalt attaine vnto great rewards.</hi> I saye vnto you (O you yong men) goe on for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, whether soeuer Vertue shall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you, and you shal receyue greate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, for he that hath atteyned vnto Vertue, lacketh not anye thing, but hath obtayned all things: as <hi>Plautus</hi> witnesseth, in <hi>Amphit. Comedia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:176849:41"/>
                     <head>Of prayse and threatning.</head>
                     <p>HEre in this laste and fourthe place, yong men haue their commendatiō and prayse, if they be once founde to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, and to go stil forwardes in the waye of vertue and honestie. For, praise is a gret spurring and quickning forwards, to dispatch with spéed any businesse that is taken in hand: as <hi>Ouide</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ouide.</note> recordeth in these verses folowing, in his .5. booke of sorrow. <hi>To be short</hi> (sayth he) <hi>Praise gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth great strength vnto the minde: and of prayse, loue maketh right fruitful and flowing breastes.</hi> For, we all (as sayeth <hi>Cicero</hi>) are inflamed with the desire and loue of praise: <hi>Quintilian</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Quintilian.</note> biddeth vs to commende yong men, but speciallye all such as go forwards in wel doing. But, if they shall be founde slowe to embrace Vertue and Honestie: neyther yet haue will to heare godly admonitions &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings: then must they sharpelye be dealt withal, and that with threatnings, and then with whippings, as <hi>Cicero</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:176849:41"/> in his fourth booke of his newe Rethoricke, saying in this maner: They whiche thinke that yong men oughte to be forgiuen of their crimes and offēces, are much deceyued: bycause that theyr age is no let or impediment to the doyng of any goodnesse: for they are then as apt to learne good things, as they are to the contrarie, euil things. But those in déede do very wisely, which minister vnto yōg men sharpe correction: that they in theyr ripe and flourishing age, maye atteyne vnto such vertues, as may afterwardes defende them during the time of theyr whole life.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the dueties of yong men.</head>
                  <p>THe dueties of yong men, are diuers to be vnderstanded. And the first is, how that they ought to choose vnto them selues, suche a kinde of life, as they wil endeauour still to vse euen vnto theyr graue, after the example of <hi>Hercules:</hi> of whom it is read, how he in the time of his youth, dyd the very same thing: and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176849:42"/> after the custome of the Romaines, who also brought their yong men into the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon market place (when they were something growen vnto yeares) &amp; there they clothed them (as before is noted) in a mannes gowne: that they might then begin to throwe their Nuttes abroade, wherewith long before they had played and passed forth their time: and shoulde also put from them the follie of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer age, and shoulde hunte after that life, which is of all men most worthilye commended. For, it behoueth a man, not to passe the way of Honestie and of good life, whiche of necessitie must here lyue amongst men.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as <hi>Tullie</hi> witnesseth in his first booke of <hi>Offices:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> It is the parte of a yong man to reuerence his elders: and to choose out from amongst them, the beste and most approued: by whose coūsell and honestie, he may best order and gouerne his life: Let him well temper himselfe from lewde luste, and from foolish coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous desires. Let him exercise himself in labour, and in patience also both of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:176849:42"/> mynde and bodie: that he may be apte to be a man of warre, yea, and a Senator also. And when he will refresh himself, and giue him selfe vnto pastime and ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: let him then take héede of intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauncie: let him remember the Vertue of bashfulnesse: neyther let him be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much Prodigall or giuen vnto wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, but rather vnto shamefastnesse: and chieflye in those things, where hys elders shal be presente. These are the words of <hi>Tullie.</hi> Furthermore, let yong men thinke themselues (in time and in place) to be men, and not beastes: and therefore shoulde they also haue better manners than beastes. Let them call to minde that they are yong men, and not boyes and children to do things childish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: neyther that they be men and aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes, and so to thinke themselues wyse ynough in their owne conceiptes: but that they also stande in néede to haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction and counsayle.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:176849:43"/>
                     <head>Of Mannes age.</head>
                     <p>THe fifte age, is called, the valiaunt or manlike state of mankinde: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering, that at this time, both the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, age, and body of man is now fullye ripe and growen vp: so that it hath ceas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to grow any further in youthfulnes: and that also the beard hath now appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on his Chinne. This (truely) is the only age, whiche is moste to be applyed vnto Vertue and Honesty: for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> it nowe flourisheth in the vnderstanding of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, &amp; is also strong in bodie, that it may the rather embrace the way of Vertue: bycause by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of this age (that is to witte) of a man, Vertue hadde first hys name. For, when to this word, <hi>Vir,</hi> ther is also added this sillable, <hi>Tus,</hi> thys worde <hi>Ʋirtus</hi> is sayde to be made. So that Vertue hath borowed hir name of a man, that is to say, of <hi>Vir,</hi> bicause that only man is a most apte or fit minister, and a worshipper of Vertue.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:176849:43"/>
                  <head>Of the Honest life of Man.</head>
                  <p>THe life (truely) of a man, ought to be verye honest, and to be fully repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with Vertue. For, he leadeth not (as he ought) the life of an Honest man, which kéepeth not all good Vertues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, but offendeth yet stil in some. Let a man therfore be prudent, Iust, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, strong, and of valiaunt courage: And let him be prudent, that he maye wisely dispose his wordes: call also to minde former déedes committed, wel to order things present: and before hande wisely to loke about him, to prouide for things that are to come. And let him be wel ware, that what so euer he taketh in hand to do, that it may be done of him wisely and discretely, &amp; to haue alwaies an eye vnto the ende. For (doubtlesse, as <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> sayeth:) It is a shame to saye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ende: I would not haue thought, that it wuld so come to passe. Therfore, <hi>Terence</hi> in his <hi>Adelphus</hi> saith: This is it to be wise: not onelye to prouide for thinges before our eies: but for suche
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:176849:44"/> things also as are yet for to come. Let him deale iustlye with all menne, doe hurte to no man, nor wrong anye man: Lette him be friendlye to others, and a louer also of peace and concorde: Lette him likewise be godlye, and of curteous behauiour: and in all things lette him loue constancie, and kepe sure his credite:<note place="margin">Credite.</note> for credite (as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> in his .1. booke of <hi>Offices</hi> reporteth) is the foundatiō or ground worke of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice. Let him be moderate in al things, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is, in kéeping of Temperance and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: let him be also modest, &amp; of chaste &amp; moderate disposition: let him be a spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and no prodigal spender, sober also in all his doings, and inclined to bashful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Let him be puissaunte and strong: not so muche in bodye, as specially in the minde: and not fearful, or of a weake harte in time of aduersitie, neyther let hym giue place vnto euil: but let hym alwayes preuayle with the greater boldnesse or stoutnesse of courage: lette hym not be sodaynely moued eyther fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: but, how so euer things do fal out,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176849:44"/> lette hym plucke vppe vnto him a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and manly heart. And aboue al things, lette hym brydle in himselfe, the notorious euilles of Auarice and Ire. Lette him not desire vaine and foolish thinges, as the manner is of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: and when he is moued vnto anger, lette him then refraine and not doe anye thing. <hi>Plato</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plato.</note> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on a certaine time being demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, what man (amongst others) was most strong: aunswered and sayde: Hée is moste strong that can ouercome hys owne furye or anger. Furthermore, let hym that desireth the vse or way of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty, obserue these two precepts: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is, that he firste should séeke means to be in déede suche a one (or the verye same) as he woulde gladlye desire to bée accompted off. For, <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> witnesseth in his seconde booke of <hi>Offices,</hi> howe <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> was wonte to saye: The way to glorye was but shorte, if a man would studye to bée suche a one in déede, as hée woulde bée counted of others.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:176849:45"/> Secondly, let hym earnestly labour (as out of this precept of <hi>Ouid:</hi>) that he lose not the name of a good man. <hi>If thou lose</hi> (sayth he) <hi>all things: yet remember too keepe sure thy good name and fame: for if that be once lost, thou shalt afterwards bee but slenderlye accompted of.</hi> And that this may of euery man be done, let this rule now folowing of <hi>Horace</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horace.</note> in his Epistle be truely obserued: that is, <hi>Bee not to hasty: but before thou goest about any matter, pause a certaine time, and aske coūsel of the learned, after what sort and maner thou maiest quietly passe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the course of thy time and age.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of old Age.</head>
                     <p>NOwe, the <hi>.6.</hi> and last age, is called olde Age: vnto which age, properly belongeth the vertue of prudence: which Vertue, olde men haue atteyned vnto, eyther by custome of long life, eyther by Knowledge, or else by greate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Wherefore, It is the duetyes of Olde menne (sayeth <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:176849:45"/> in his <hi>.1.</hi> of Offices,<note place="margin">Cicero</note> to further and helpe with their Councell and Wisedome, both Youthful persons, their Friendes also, and the Common wealth. Therefore, <hi>Romulus,</hi> the firste buylder of the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> chose oute (as <hi>Liuie</hi> witnesseth) an hundreth olde men, whiche shoulde gouerne the same Citie with Councel and Prudence. And thereof (euen of olde men) is the Senate appointed and ordayned, as it were the gathering togyther a companye of olde and aged men: to the ende they shoulde be Gouernours of Cities, and to be an example also of Vertue and Honestie vnto all those that be of the yonger sorte. Therefore is Honor giuen vnto them, as vnto the Possessoures and Teachers of Prudence, by the Image of Vertue and Honestie. Finally, it is the duetye of Olde men, to auoide the Vice of Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice (which chiefly raigneth in thē:) and that done, to eschue Waiwardnes &amp; the sin of Slouthfulnesse. And it is al wayes their partes to consider, what the white haires on their heades do truely signifie
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:176849:46"/> vnto them, and what also their crooked bodies do prognosticate vnto them: that is to wit, that their maners (apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) be both graue and good: and that they likewise remember, howe they doe daily drawe nighe vnto Death, and are euen nowe leaning ouer the Graue or Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre. Their bodies do bend euē towards the Earth: whereby they maye truelye knowe, that immediately after Death, they shall descende into the bowelles of the Earth. It behoueth them therefore to forsake the toies and allurementes of this vaine worlde, and to prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vnto the houre of Death: And let them likewise ponder well this saying of <hi>Horace</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>orace.</note> in their minde: <hi>Thou haste nowe playde ynoughe, and thou haste drunke ynoughe: it is time therefore for thee that thou departest hence: leaste wanton Youth doe laughe at thee when hee seeth thee drunke: and so giue thee a dry scoffe and scorne thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:176849:46"/>
               <head>VVhat Honestie best becommeth vs, both towardes God and Men. CHAP. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He knowledge of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Honestie, do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all (or very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle profite) vnlesse it bée exercised or put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise. For, <hi>Cicero</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> in his firste Booke of Offices thus reporteth, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the whole praise of Vertue, cōsisteth not in Knowledge, but in very Practise. And in the .3. booke of Friēdship he saith: that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reward &amp; frute of Vertue is then most of all taken, when it is bestowed vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of his neighboures. For, the action of Vertue, is as well bestowed vpon God, as vpon Men: bicause we are borne both for the seruice of God, &amp; for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seruice of Men: Yet one kind of Honestie is due to God, &amp; an other is due to Men.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:176849:47"/>
                  <head>What best becommeth vs to do to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Almightie God.</head>
                  <p>HGnestie towardes God, consisteth eyther in the true Worship of God, or else in pure Religion. For, as <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactantius.</note> in his thirde Booke recordeth, wée muste haue respecte vnto Religion: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, whosoeuer receiueth not, hée ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth himselfe here vpon the Earth: hée followeth the way of Beastes: and abandoneth himselfe from all Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For, all Wisedome in this onelye thing consisteth: that is, that hée truelye knowe God, and duely worshippe hym. And rightly to serue God, is nothing else than to kéepe and maintayne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse, with the vse of good workes. Wherefore, if a manne should demaund of hym, whyche is willing to bée indéede truly Wise,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>he cause <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>hy vvee <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ere born</note> and for what cause hée was borne: hée shall answere (and that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily) without feare: that hée was borne to worshippe GOD: who therefore did beget vs, euen that we should serue him
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:176849:47"/> and worshippe him. These wordes are taken out of <hi>Lactantius.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactantius.</note> Therefore, the olde and auntient Romanes, didde dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and religiouslie obserue the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe of God, as <hi>Valerius</hi> and <hi>Liuie</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where doe shewe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What becommeth vs to doe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Men.</head>
                  <p>NOwe, after God, Vertue and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie is to bée giuen and exhibited vnto menne. For, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth in his sixte Booke. The firste office of Righteousnesse is, to be ioyned wyth God: and the next with Mā. And Christ in his Gospel commandeth, saying: Loue the Lorde thy God, and thy Neyghbour as thy selfe. One manne vnto an other, oughte to be (as it were) a God: both in the vse of Mercie, of Courtesie, and in Godlinesse: thereby to shewe forth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and help vnto the afflicted and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse: and to bestowe foode vppon suche as want or be in necessitie, according to the minde of <hi>Lactantius.</hi> But, what
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:176849:48"/> thing wée owe vnto euerye manne, the discourse nowe following will playnely shewe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What our duetie is, towards the whole Countrey.</head>
                  <p>HEre, amongst menne, our Country occupieth the firste place. Whyche, the olde Philosophers (as saith the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher <hi>Philelphus</hi> in his fourth Booke <hi>Of the Education of Children</hi>) did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre before oure Parentes: bycause we are more bound vnto our Country: than vnto our Parents. <hi>Plato</hi> therefore said, that the Countrey chalengeth parte of our birth: and the cause is, that wée are borne to profite oure Countrey. For, by fiue sundry things, wée maye profite the Citizens of our common wealth or coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The first is, euen to laboure for his owne honour and praise: in this, that wée endeuour to be made suche maner of persons (and to continue also such) as may in time to come, be an honor vnto his Countrey: and to obtaine also of it,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:176849:48"/> both Honor, Laude and Praise.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to instructe the Countrey <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> (if it be vnlearned, rude, and foolishe) in Prudence and in Councell: for it is our dutie to teache the blinde and ignorant.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to endeuour oure selues (as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> muche as in vs lyeth) to benefite that same Coast and Countrey, wherein wée were borne, nourished, and broughte vp.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, to defende it, by oure Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and strength: as time and necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie shall conueniently requyre.</p>
                  <p>Fiftely, if it shall so be néedefull, (and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> if the Countrey cannot otherwise be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended) we oughte alwayes to be ready, euen to dye for the same, which Death, of all other deathes, is counted moste honest. And herevpon <hi>Horace</hi> sayeth: It is right swéete and comely, to dye for our Countrey. Whiche thing, manye of the Gentiles haue done, as in <hi>Liuie</hi> a man may sée.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:176849:49"/>
                  <head>What oure duetie is, towards oure Parentes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> AFter GOD and our Countrie, oure Parentes are of vs to be reuerenced and worshipped: as both Holy and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane writings do bidde and commande vs. And we ought also to worship them, bothe in Vertue and Honestie. And wée muste also commend vnto our Parentes fiue orders of Honestie: that is, Firste, we must obey them in all honest things. Secondely, according to oure abilitie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> we muste doe them seruice. Thirdelye, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> by honouring them, whether in Words or in Déedes. But we maye not curse them, nor once speake against them. In all oure déedes, countenaunces, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, we muste reuerently come bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed vnto them, and that with courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> bowing the Knée. Fourthly, that by thus beautifying of them, throughe our good and duetifull going forwardes in Vertue and Knowledge, they may also, by oure meanes be sometimes honoured
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:176849:49"/> of others: neyther maye wée in any wise once decline from their example of good Maners and honestie of Life. Fiftely, by chearishing also of them, if they chaunce <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> to fall into Pouertie, or into Olde Age: for, bothe brute Beastes and Birds, are wonte by Nature so to doe: chiefly the Storke, who (in suche maner) doe féede and nourishe their aged and old Parēts. And <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> in his Booke of Orations, sayeth: that Godlinesse is nothing else but Loue and Courtesie towardes oure Parentes. And <hi>Franciscus Philelphus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philelphus.</note> in his fourth Booke and thirde Chapter <hi>Of the Education of Children,</hi> doe euen so saye of the Dueties of Children to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their Parentes. That although we be neuer able with like goodnesse to requite them: yet, as muche as lyeth in our abilitie and power, wée ought duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to doe oure diligence vnto them, well to vse them, continually to attende vppon them, to giue eare vnto them, to hearken vnto their exhortations, to obey their commandements, and to allow al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so &amp; receiue their wils &amp; consultations, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:176849:50"/> as they were the wordes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of Almightie God: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be that wée shoulde stay or abide for them, or yéeld vnto that they do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, eyther else touching the state of Marriage: neyther maye wée wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande them when they be angrye: and if they threatē or terrifye vs, we oughte with patience to beare it. And when they will vs to do things that are disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and vnlawfull, wée maye not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouslye refuse them: but gentlye, modestly, and withoute anye kinde of murmuring, banning or cursing. These wordes are taken out of <hi>Philelphus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What successe they haue had, whiche haue bin disobedient vnto their Parentes.</head>
                  <p>AS old Writers do testifie, those chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whiche were disobedient vnto their Parentes, had neuer good successe, neither well prospered in this worlde. It is read of <hi>Orestes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Orestes.</note> the Grecian, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:176849:50"/> hée slewe his Mother, he was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a furie of Hell. <hi>Nero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nero.</note> also the Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> bycause hée killed his Mother, was accounted a most cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and mercilesse Tyraunte. In olde time, in the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> the slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Parentes by their owne Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, was most grieuously plagued and punished: that is to say, suche murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers were shutte vppe or tyed in a Sacke made of Leather: wherein was a Dogge prepared, a Serpent, and also an house Cocke: and so were they all togither caste into the depth of the Sea.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What beste becommeth vs towards our Schoolemaisters and Teachers.</head>
                  <p>NExt after our Parents, our School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maysters also are of vs to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped. For our Schoolemaisters are vnto vs our second Parents. Therefore, Gentilitie would, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Maysters should be to vs in stéede of our Parents (as sayeth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:176849:51"/>
                     <hi>Iuuenall</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iuuenall.</note> in his Satyres:) bycause oure Schoolemaisters are the Parents of our Soules:<note place="margin">The life of our Soules, vvhich vve take of our Parentes, vvhat it is.</note> for they giue vnto vs the life of our Soules: that is to saye, Vertue, Knowledge, and Honestie: euen as our Parentes doe only giue vnto vs the life of our Bodies. Therefore, nexte vnto oure Parentes, are oure Schoolemay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters or Teachers: and not muche lesse than they, are they of vs duely to bée reuerenced. For, it is manifest (as saith <hi>Philelphus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philelphus.</note> in his fourth Booke and sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Chapiter) that all those whiche haue reuerenced their Schoolemaisters, haue attained vnto greate Grace, and vnto the encrease of Learning. Amongst whome (touching all men of that time) was <hi>Traianus</hi> the Emperoure, and also <hi>Caesar</hi> muche commended for their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. This manne did very muche reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence his Mayster <hi>Plutarche. Marcus Antonius</hi> also (of all Princes the moste deuoute Romaine) made in his house pictures of Golde, to represente before him, his Schoolemaisters and teachers. <hi>Cicero</hi> being made the Prince of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:176849:51"/> (bycause it was thoughte, that there was none more Eloquent than hée in the Latine Tong) doeth in his bookes extoll by name his Maisters and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. And so many as haue attained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the toppe and perfection of Learning, Honestie, and Worthinesse, haue bothe worshipped, greately loued, and praised their Maisters.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of those whiche haue dishonoured their Maisters and Teachers.</head>
                  <p>ANd (as saith <hi>Philelphus</hi>) all such as haue dishonoured their Schoolemai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and Teachers, haue alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned both ignoraunt and most beast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Amongst whom, <hi>Nero</hi> that gracelesse Prince, is imputed as chiefe and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall: whom all writers do accuse for his haynous and horrible Vices. This <hi>Nero</hi> was he that slewe his Mayster <hi>Seneca. Beroaldus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Beroaldus.</note> in his Prouerbiall Oration doeth saye: He that by the backbiting of hys Schoolemayster doeth séeke to get a name, moste worthily (by it) findeth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:176849:52"/> shame and is hissed at, and as a wicked manne is remoued out of the companye of all honest and good menne: for, hée is to be feared as a Viper: and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to bée made a common hatred, than he whiche curseth or raileth on his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes. For, the Maister is the Parent, yea, the fashioner &amp; the framer of mens mindes. Whome, vnlesse we (wyth all our good spéeches and wordes) doe extoll and commende: and, vnlesse (in euerye place, and amongst all menne) wée doe sette him foorthe with honourable praise and reporte, wée shall moste iustely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue to be called both vngodly, wicked, and verye gracelesse. These bée the wordes of <hi>Beroaldus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Dueties towardes Maisters.</head>
                  <p>TOwardes Maisters therefore, these foure dueties are to be considered. Firste, that wée loue them, euen as we shoulde oure Parentes. Secondlye, wée oughte to obey them, and to agrée vnto them in all things which are honest, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:176849:52"/> in fulfilling of their commaundements. Thirdly, that wée ought euer to be thāk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto them, euen vntil the ende of our liues. And fourthly, that we must di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently labour, that we may in time to come, either be like vnto them in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Knowlege: or else (if it possibly maye be) that we maye passe and excell them. So, manye in times paste were made more skilful than their Maysters: as <hi>Beroaldus</hi> maketh boaste, howe that hée had otherwhiles some Schoolemay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, whyche in course of time, he went in Knowledge farre beyonde them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What Dueties we do owe vnto our Alies and Kinsfolkes.</head>
                  <p>THe reason or true rule of Nature, will moste easely and plainly shew, of what good maner and disposition wée oughte to bée towardes oure Kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes, and vnto suche as bée of alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance vnto vs: as towards our bréethren and sisters, whyche in bloude are
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:176849:53"/> linked vnto vs, bothe touching Father and Mother: and that we shold towards them be of like affection, as we alwayes vse to be towardes oure owne selues: bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are (as it were) nothing els, saue onely euen the verye same that wée oure selues are: for they are partes and members of oure owne bloud, and of our owne stocke and offspring. Wherefore, wée shoulde none otherwise accompte of them, than as proper members of our owne bodyes: and that wée also ought to putte awaye farre from them all suche thynges, as wée woulde not wishe to oure owne bodyes, or vnto oure owne proper members in anye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specte: for, otherwise, there is no iuste cause why wée shoulde be counted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: euen as he that more fauoureth one parte of his bodye than an other, is in déede truelye counted but fonde and foolishe: so shall hée worthilye bée cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnkynde, whyche neyther helpeth nor councelleth all suche, as bée mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ioyned vnto him in Linage &amp; Kinred. Al these thyngs doth the law of Nature
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:176849:53"/> both shewe and streightly commaunde vnto vs. And commaundement is also giuen vnto vs in the Gospel of Christe, that our neyghbour (of vs) is to be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, euen as we would loue our selues. And truely, they are to be estéemed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neare neyghbours vnto vs, which are so ioyned vnto vs in kindred and bloude.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Our dueties tovvardes our friendes.</head>
                     <p>NOw, in the .5. place, our friends are to be reuerenced and worshipped. And therein, what kinde of Honestie and comelinesse is due vnto them, the wrightings of learned men doe most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly teach: and chiefely, <hi>Cicero,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> in his booke of Frendship and Amitie. And among friendes, 6. things are chiefly (as lawes) to be obserued and kept. The first <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is, (as <hi>Cicero</hi> alledgeth) that we shoulde not aske of our friendes things that are dishonest, but only things Honest: &amp; for our friendes cause or pleasure, we maye not do things dishonest, but only things
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:176849:54"/>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> good and honest. The seconde is, how we muste in prosperitie reioyce wyth oure friendes: and we must be mery and glad with them, when anye good thing shall chance vnto them: and that none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, than if they shoulde chaunce vnto our selues. And in their aduersitie also we should be sory for them, and stil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte them with oure good comforte and help: and not then to forsake them after the manner of Swallowes:<note place="margin">Svvallovvs</note> whyche (as <hi>Cicero</hi> witnesseth in his fourth booke of newe Rethoricke) are in Sommer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye at hande, but so soone as they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue Winter comming, they then do al <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> fly as fast away. And thirdly, let vs (both we and our friends) always wil, and not will, one only, and the selfe same thing: And let also all our dilectations and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies be euermore one. For, vnlikenesse of studies, and diuersitie of manners, do still breake and departe friendshippe in sunder: as <hi>Cicero</hi> witnesseth in hys booke of Friendshippe, and <hi>Horace</hi> in his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Epistles. Fourthly, we shoulde doe none other thing to our friende, than we wold
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:176849:54"/> wishe vnto our selues: for as <hi>Cicero</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: a friende is none other thing, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the verye same. And true friendes doubtlesse, are one onlye hearte in two breasts: let vs therfore loue them as our selues: and louing them, let vs labour to winne and ouercome them, and not (by it) to be ouercome of them: for that were a thing most dishonest. Fiftlye, <hi>Cicero</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cicero.</note>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> commaundeth, that friendshippe ought to be performed, not for hope of reward, gaine or profitte (as the nature is of the common people:) whych, when commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie once ceasseth, they put awaye also therewith theyr Friendshippe, and their mutuall loue and fauoure: But true Friendshippe in déede, is to bée putte in the onelye loue of the hearte: for then wyll it the longer continue and stande sure: and wée shall thereby bée the more redy, franckly to giue vnto our friends, than to looke for a benefyte at hys hande. The sixte and last lawe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> is, howe that wee oughte to vse towards our Friendes, louyng and fayre speache: for, as <hi>Terence</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Terence.</note> witnesseth:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:176849:55"/> Flatterye getteth friendes. And y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> done, we may not vpbrayde our friendes, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom we haue at any time bestowed a benefit or good turne: for, <hi>Cicero</hi> saith, such a kinde of men are muche to be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whiche doe caste another man in the téeth with their good tournes whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they bestowed vppon him: for that man which hadde them bestowed vppon hym, ought rather himself to haue them in remembraunce, and not he that firste did bestowe them: for, in the first booke of olde Rethoricke, the same <hi>Cicero</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> sayth: that he is verye shamelesse and vnwise, which for a benefit bestowed, requireth, not only thankes, but also reward or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence. But, if any fauour haue bene shewed vnto vs, <hi>Cicero</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>icero.</note> in his <hi>Offices</hi> cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, howe that we ought then to follow the manner of the fruitful fields, which yéeldeth forth againe muche more than before it receyued of the Sower. Euen so, in friendship, if we maye, wée ought much rather to giue more again, than before was bestowed vpon vs. Or else we may say: It is not in our powers
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:176849:55"/> to requite with equal ballaunce, or with such measure as before we did receyue: yet are we willyng to be dutifully thāk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if Fortune at any time hereafter, shall more plentifullye and friendlye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vs.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Dueties towards our Aequals or fellowes.</head>
                  <p>THat kind of Familiaritie amongst men, which is called fellowship,<note place="margin">Felovvship vvhat it is.</note> is most like vnto friendship. For, fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe is nothing else, than a friendly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie or friendship of men, ioyned with consent togither amōg themselues. But in choosing, and in making much of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, we ought chiefly to do our good endeauour, that only the honest and good be choosen or had in company: and with whom, we also our selues may be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and made better.<note place="margin">Hovv vve should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our selues, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard our cōpanions.</note> And whē we haue once gotten vnto vs suche companions, we muste then so behaue our selues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them, that we passe not in any wise, these .6. precepts folowing. And the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:176849:56"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> first is, that we be none otherwise min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded towards them, than vnto our verye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> friends. Secondly, we must obserue these fiue things, which <hi>Terence</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Terence.</note> mentioneth in <hi>Andria:</hi> that is to say, we must learne patiently to sustayne and suffer, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, customes and gestures of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions &amp; fellows: &amp; not sodainely to be moued to anger for a word or two: but to suffer quietly al things, &amp; that with a patient minde &amp; cheareful countenance. And that once done, how we should giue our selues altogither vnto the friendlye beckes and good wils of our louing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdlye, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we must obey vnto their goodwils and wishes: and also to do that, which they themselues go about, if (at the least) without any tricke of disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty. Therfore also is the old common prouerb here set down: that is, how we must take héed &amp; beware, that we be not offēsiue to the maners of such as be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent with vs: or els (as some saye) to the disgracing of oure owne manners.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthlye, we maye not contende with anye manne: but we muste shun
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:176849:56"/> and auoyde strife, dissentiō, brawling, or variance: neither may we sow abrode any discorde or debate. Fiftlye, we maye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> not prefer our selues before others: but to iudge alwayes others to be better thā our selues: or at the least, equal with our selues. And herevpon ariseth thys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon saying: that among companions and fellowes, there is no set or prescript order, but equalitie ought to be amongst them, and no preferring of one before another. And vnto these rules, maye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two be added. The first is, that our <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> fellowes being absent, we do not backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite them. And the seconde is, if at anye time they doe amisse, we muste courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> reprehende them, and that in a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete place, but not before others: for, otherwise, it were muche to be blamed, and not commended: and a mean truely, rather to do harme, than friendlye to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme a friend. Friends do secretlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reproue him that doth amisse: but suche as be enuious and disdainefull, doe it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:176849:57"/>
                  <head>Of Dueties towardes olde men.</head>
                  <p>VNto old Age, and vnto the antiente and graye headed, the shewe of all honestie is specially due. For they (by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of their olde and graue yeares) are to be honored: through which long time, they are thought to haue attayned vnto much prudence, both by good skil, by vse also, and by much experience. Therefore are they to be honoured, euen as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houses of Prudence. And there be thrée things, by the whiche olde men bée <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> muche beautifyed. The firste is, howe <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> in his <hi>Offices</hi> commandeth, that laboues and trauels should vnto them be deminished: bicause, through their old age, they are spoyled and depriued of the strength of their bodies. The seconde is, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that they are to be worshipped wyth séemely and chaste words, and to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with louing and friendlye termes: namely, as vse teacheth vs, wyth thys name, Father or Mother. They oughte not (of anye) to be reprehended, as are
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:176849:57"/> those, which be wicked and lewde Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets: and before their presence, nothing shoulde be spoken or done, which should not be good and Honest. Herevpon, <hi>Ouid</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> sayth: <hi>In times past, there was giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hoare headed men, great worship and reuerence: &amp; then an old wrinckled face, was much esteemed and accompted of. Who then durst speake anye wordes worthy blushing, or to be ashamed of, before an antient and graue old man. For olde age (in those dayes) was of suche e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils most readie to be reuenged.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> they are of righte to be reuerenced with honest déeds and comely gestures,<note place="margin">The sharp punishment of disreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent youth against old age.</note> that is, either by bending the knée before them, or else reuerently to vncouer theyr heades, Which thing, in olde time, the Romains toke order to be done, making therto this law: that if any man shoulde passe by an olde and auntient man wyth his heade couered, he shoulde therefore (by iudgemente) haue his heade stricken off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:176849:58"/>
                  <head>Of Dueties towards Women.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> HOnour (for two speciall causes) is due also vnto all Honest and good women: The first cause is, for that they are our Mothers and Nurses: &amp; bycause they haue more sweate, labour and care in bringing vp of children, than Fathers vse to haue. Secondly, bycause they vse <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> greatly to extol the Vertue of womenly shamefastnesse, or gift of chastity: which noble and worthy Vertue, is very much of them estéemed, as it is euident amōg many worthy Matrones, mentioned of the Historie writers. Worship therfore is due vnto them, after thrée sundrye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> kindes of Honesty. First of al, men must abstein from laciuiousnesse and wanto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> communication: for, where as they thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues be chastly giuen, there ought not anye thing be spoken or vttered in theyr <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> presence, but onlye that, whiche is both pure,<note place="margin">Hovv men <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ught to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ehaue <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>emselues in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of vvomen.</note> chaste and Honest. Secondlye, we must abstaine from vnséemely gestures and maners: which are meanes to bréed
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:176849:58"/> corruption. Nothing of vs should be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted without the Vertue of shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastnesse. For, it alwayes behoueth vs, expresly to vtter in our manners those only things, which are most conuenient for our state and condition, as time and place requireth. Therfore, for so much, as women are counted such, as do make much of womāly shamefastnes &amp; chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: truely, it behoueth vs also (beyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them) to be very modest, shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and of chaste disposition. Thirdlye,<note place="margin">The armor of Patience tovvardes vvomen.</note> we maye not be cruel againste women, with an armed or angry hande: wheras they themselues are vnarmed and but of féeble force: neyther ar they by nature strong ynough to resist him that beateth them: And there is also no commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatiō vnto him, that doth ouercome a womā, either séeketh to be reuēged of hir, as the common Prouerbe is, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned of <hi>Virgil,</hi> in the second <hi>Aeneid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:176849:59"/>
                     <head>Of Dueties tovvardes For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainers and straungers.</head>
                     <p>NOwe, towarde straungers and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landishmenne, the Dueties and Offices of Vertues are to be kept: chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly, foure in number: namelie, touching <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the firste, they are to be receyued of vs with verye reuerente and courteous wordes, and wyth friendelye entertayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: that they maye the rather knowe, howe they are come vnto a company of men, and amongst men indéede, and not among cruel and wicked beastes: Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they to be mocked of vs, or scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at with wordes. And herevpon saith <hi>Plautus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Plautus.</note> in his Comedie called <hi>Penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus:</hi> Thou must in this case (sayth he) bée as a seruaunt both wicked and euil: for a man being a stranger, and an Aliant, why doest thou laugh at hym or scorne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> hym? The seconde is, in instructing of them in those things, whereof (in our Countrey) they be yet ignoraunte: and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:176849:59"/> not as though we woulde deceyue them by our coniecture in such things whyche are vsual amongst vs, and whereof they haue already knowledge: for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaseth not vnto vs any commendation at all, but rather reproche and discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: For it is an easie thing to deceiue the ignoraunt: <hi>Erasmus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Erasmus.</note> in hys booke of the Instruction of a Christian Prince, hath thys saying, that <hi>Plato</hi> in times paste did saye: howe we ought to take diligente héede, that we hurte not straungers more than Citizens: bycause that straungers being destitute of the helpe of all their friendes and kinsfolks, are the more subiecte vnto iniuries and wrongs. Therefore also thoughte the Gentiles, that <hi>Iupiter</hi> was the reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the iniuries of straungers: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they called hym <hi>Xenium.</hi> Thirdlye, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that we must shew the right waye vnto such as séeke it, and are ignoraunt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and not leade them on the left hande, where as they shoulde goe on the righte hand: for that were a déed most wicked, to deceiue a straunger, not reaping at al
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:176849:60"/> thereby any benefite or commoditie: for that becommeth rather théeues and ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fians, who willinglye byddeth the straunger to goe out of the waye: whereby they maye fall into theyr Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and so to be kylled of them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthelye, wée muste also receiue them to haue lodging amongst vs: and to suffer them likewise to haue theyr dwelling with vs. And for this cause, did the Heathen worshippe Hospitality, euen as it wer an holy and sacred thing,<note place="margin">Hospitality cōmended.</note> and called <hi>Iupiter</hi> the God of Hospitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or of Harborowe: and that bycause it was a thing both godlye and holye, to entertayne straungers and Forrainers. Therfore did Quéene <hi>Dido</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Dido.</note> of <hi>Carthage</hi> (as it appeareth in the firste booke of <hi>Aeneidos</hi>) whilest that shée entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Aeneas</hi> in Harborowe and vnto a bankette, wyth other of the <hi>Troy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> call vppon <hi>Iupiter,</hi> as it were one that dutifully giueth righte vnto straungers. And the olde Romaines receiued into their Cytie many straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:176849:60"/> who also at length were made Rulers of the Citie, as sayeth <hi>Lyuie,</hi> concernyng the buyldyng of the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <hi>Beroaldus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Beroaldus.</note> also wrighteth: that in doyng anye busynesse, or in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng anye seruice, Pylgrimes and Straungers were firste preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Alies and kinsfolkes. Yea, and at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Office of a king, of a Consull and Preator, was gyuen vnto Straungers: as in <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> and <hi>Tarquinius</hi> time we so reade of manye Straungers and Forray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. They hadde also vnto theyr Pretor, a Straunger, who was a Lawe giuer vnto Straungers.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:176849:61"/>
                  <head>Dueties towardes our Enimies.</head>
                  <p>TOwardes our aduersaries also, we ought to be mindefull of the vse of Vertue: and chiefly therein to vse foure <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> precepts.<note place="margin">Promise vnto our enimies is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued.</note> The first is (as <hi>Cicero</hi> willeth vs in his <hi>Offices</hi>) that if promise be once made towardes our enimies, it ought by all meanes to be kept: as the lawe and custome is of Gentlemen euen at thys daye. Of whome, who so euer was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken prisoner, and yet let goe frée: vnto the same he oughte to retourne agayne with thankfulnes: for otherwise, he is to be put out of the number of noble &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> gentlemen. Secondlye, being stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp and prouoked through iniurie, or by war proclaymed and denounced: wée shoulde not therefore immediately resist them or byghte them agayne: for that is the propertie of beastes: but courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouslye at the firste to handle the matter wyth good communication and speache, as <hi>Terence</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Terence.</note> witnesseth in <hi>Eunuchus:</hi> It becommeth a wise man, firste to proue
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:176849:61"/> the matter with wordes, and after that with weapons: for nothing ought to be done rashely, or vppon anger or sodaine furie.</p>
                  <p>Thirdely, that it is better to forgiue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> (if we haue iniurie offered vnto vs) than with the like to requite the same. For, to forgiue, is a more noble kind of reuēge, than to requite like for like. <hi>Erasmus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Erasmus.</note> sayth in his Booke <hi>Of the Instruction of a Christian Prince:</hi> that Punishemente and Reuenge, is a signe but of a weake and childishe minde. And <hi>Iuuenal</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iuuenal.</note> in his twelfth Satyre sayth: that touching Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, no man reioiceth so much therein as doth a woman: and is therefore (in that respecte) noted as one vnworthy of any commendation and praise.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, if wée cannot driue away <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the iniuries and assaultes of our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, vnlesse with the like strength we doe resiste them: then the saying of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> is to be followed: that is, whether it be GOD, or whether it be harde For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune that doth call, let vs contentedlye followe the same. Chaunce and Vertue
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:176849:62"/> are intermingled in one. We must ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore resiste with Armoure and Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and that stoutlye and bolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: as <hi>Liuius</hi> euery where writeth of the Romaine Nation. Yet that saying of <hi>Cicero</hi> is alwayes to be accounted of: and that for no other cause, than that we may afterwardes liue in peace, and not to be reuenged of oure aduersaries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Dueties towardes oure Maisters, whome we serue.</head>
                  <p>TOwardes our bodily Maisters (by whose breade we here liue, and to whom also we owe seruice) we haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> thereto foure maner of dueties. And the first is, that readily and with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to execute their willes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, we muste be alwayes trustie and sure: and not go about their businesse slouthfully or créepinglie like a Snaile: for nothing shoulde be done eyther loytringly, or painefully, eyther yet ydlely, during such time as we haue
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:176849:62"/> to doe aboute oure Maisters businesse. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondlye, we muste be verye faithfull and trustie towardes them, and in no wise to deceiue or beguile them, neither yet to defraude them by flatterie, nor in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> their absence to hate them. Thirdely, wée should be also profitable vnto them, and stand thē alwaies in suche stéede, as dutifully of vs is requyred: taking like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise sure héede to preuent occasions of their disprofite or hinderaunce: and so to séeke rather for their profite and commoditie, than for our owne: yea, and sooner to execute oure Maisters bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse, thā to attend vpon our own mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And if we once perceiue our Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, in daunger, to sustaine any sodayne losse or hynderaunce (by what meanes soeuer) we then being seruauntes, ought (as muche as in vs doth lye) to remoue the same cause. These, or the like are the sayings of <hi>Plautus.</hi> Fourthly, we ought to be silent or of fewe wordes, and that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> for two sundry causes. The firste is, not to aunsweare ouerthwartlye vnto the wordes of oure Mayster, althoughe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:176849:63"/> we séeme (in some things) to haue better knowledge than he hathe: neyther yet maye wée be vtterly dumbe, or voide of reuerent spéeche, when wée haue cause to speake. Herevppon sayth <hi>Plautus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plautus.</note> in the Comedie of the bragging Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: that it is the parte of a Seruaunt, to know alwayes more thā he speaketh. Secondly, not to reueale or discouer our Maisters secreates vnto anye others, or to publishe them abroade withoute the doores. For Silence vnto a seruaunt is a greate commendation and praise.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Dueties towardes Magistrates.</head>
                  <p>DVetie of Vertue, is euermore due vnto the Magistrates of the same place or places, where we doe liue or haue oure being: yea, wée maye chiefly say, that it is a thréefolde Dutie. Firste, to the ende that wée shoulde obey their commaundementes and honest Lawes, we shoulde be no lawe breakers, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient vnto the Lawe.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>avves <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>hat they <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e.</note> For, the Lawes are nothing else, but Rules to liue well
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:176849:63"/> by. Truely, we liue much amisse, when (after the maner of Beastes) we do liue withoute Lawe. Neyther yet is it good and prosperous to resiste or rise agaynst Magistrates:<note place="margin">Defamatiō an odious euil against Maisters &amp; Gouernors</note> for (as the saying is) the Gnatte that biteth the Elephant, hathe no good successe: neyther yet the Bittie that vexeth the Eagle. Secondly, wée maye not, neyther in Worde, nor in Déede, séeke to dishonest Magistrates: For doubtlesse, it is a very daungerous thing for thée, either once to speake, or to write againste them, whiche are able to set thée to sale and to condempne thée. Neither is it comely, either in worde or in déede, once to defame or hurte them, whiche nighte and daye doe endeuoure themselues, orderly to rule and gouerne the common wealth, and euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar subiecte of the same, in a righte way and good trade of liuing. Thirdely, if they demand any tribute of vs, we must eyther giue it vnto them: or else verye courteouslye to render a good reason to the contrarie: for by that meanes are Cities &amp; Countreys alwayes defended,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:176849:64"/> preserued also, and restored: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise they would not lōg cōtinue. And as <hi>Liuius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Liuius.</note> witnesseth in his seconde Booke, from the building of the Citie: if other members of the bodye shoulde not mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster meate vnto the stomacke, they shold both togither perishe thoroughe hunger. So in like maner also, if Citizens and inhabitants, should not helpe their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Natiō, Princes also and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates with taxes and Tributes, they shoulde perish togither with them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>VVhat best beseemeth al degrees of men, in euery Place and Time. CHAP. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Honestie and Vertue, both Time and Place stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to greate effecte. Of whyche twoo, vnlesse there were diligent regarde to bée
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:176849:64"/> had, eyther very slenderly or nothing at all, woulde the knowledge or practice of Vertue conduce or directe to anye good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse at all. For, Time and Place (saye the Interpreters of the Scriptures) doe encrease sins: and in Time and Place, they are also againe both lightned, eased and vnburthened. So also is Vertue and Honestie, to be applied both vnto Tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Place. For, other things, and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whyche are diuers, in diuers tymes and places, are well beséeming, are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and are also to be required. But, if a manne shall not knowe, or not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe others, althoughe he hath already learned Vertue yet shall he be counted both wayes but vitious, if he knowe not howe to haue respecte vnto Time and Place. Therefore said <hi>Macrobius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Macrobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</note> in his seauenth booke of Satur. and first Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter. There is nothing so like vnto Wisedome, as to make oure spéeche apt for the tyme and place. <hi>Pittacus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pittacus.</note>
                  <hi>Mitil</hi> didde also commaunde, that the time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be noted and known: that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer we doe, we shoulde firste consider
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:176849:65"/> the aptnesse of the time. He verily did thinke, that in al things Time was best. And herevppon saide <hi>Terence:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Terence.</note> I came in Time, whiche is the chiefest thing of all other. And howe euery man may bée fit for al times and seasons, these things nowe following will plainelye disclose and open.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What is comely at a Banquet.</head>
                  <p>THe places and seasons are diuers, wherein men do here liue togyther.<note place="margin">The daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies at Banuqets.</note> But chiefly (for all that) the place and time of Banquetting, to procure appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite and immoderate luste, to lyue like common Swilbolles or vnstayed Typ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, to haue also ouermuche respect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the will of the fleshe, or likewise to sette forthe the browes of lighte and wanton countenance, is commonly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all menne verye delectable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:176849:65"/>
                  <head>We must wel iudge and weigh with our selues whilest we are drinking, sixe precepts of Vertue &amp; Honestie, alwayes to be obserued and kept: that is to say:</head>
                  <p>OF what sorte, of what wealth, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itie, the guests bée, (as saith <hi>Macrobius</hi> in his seuenth booke of <hi>Satur.</hi> the firste Chapter:) and that euery one oughte to haue also a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> eye, when time and place is conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for him to speake or not to speake, of Philosophical and waightie matters, when he is sette to be mery. Therefore <hi>Socrates</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Socrates.</note> in olde time, beyng at a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, was asked a question, to the end he should bring forth some talke, who made this answere: What things this present time requyreth, I knowe not: but such thinges as I knowe, are nothing at all fit for this present time and place: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by meaning, that wise and graue mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wherof Philoso hers did dispute in Schooles, were nothing at all méete for
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:176849:66"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the time of a Banquet. Suche men are called mery guests, which are harmlesse and no biters of men in their drinking: for, sooner at drinking than at other times (as <hi>Macrobius</hi> reporteth in hys seauenth Booke) a mans anger and sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> doeth arise and swell. In eating and drinking, measure oughte euer to be kepte, according to these twoo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes: whiche is, that meate shoulde be taken without any gluttenous desire: and drinke likewise, wythout any drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennesse. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Let these seauen rules of euery manne be kepte, according to <hi>Plautus</hi> in his Comedie of the bragging Souldior: Let him be a mery Iester and a pleasant guest, and not a detractor of another mā: let him refraine from al inconueniences: Let him speake when time requireth: Let him holde his peace when another speaketh: Lette him also spitte but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: and let him not immoderately reach <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> in his spitting. Nowe, sixtly, let him not disclose or scatter forth abroade without the doores, such things as he either séeth or heareth. Therefore <hi>Horace</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horace.</note> in his sixt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:176849:66"/> Epistle, calling his guest <hi>Torquatus,</hi> doth promise, that he wil take vpon him, howe that no manne shall spreade anye thing abroade oute of the Doores, that was talked of at the banquet. And <hi>Bero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aldus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Beroaldu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>▪</note> sayth, that the maner was of some Gentlemen, that so soone as the Guests entred into the house, they shewed vnto him the Thresholde, saying vnto him: Beyonde this nothing shall passe: that is to saye, Take héede that you tell not abroade such things vnto others, as thou haste hearde at the Table. Wherefore also in this our age, this is the custome: vpon the Table to haue painted Roses, to the ende, that vnder them, the words, whych in the time of drinking, were spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, shoulde lye close, and not be blabbed forthe abroade into any other place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Howe sober Communication, best beseemeth good Company.</head>
                  <p>IT is no easie skill, but rather great and notable, to knowe well how to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:176849:67"/> liue here amongest menne: that by the order of Friendshippe wée mighte the better please others, and that mutuall and friendly liuing togither, maye the longer remaine amongst vs: Vnto the whyche, wée haue néede of seauen In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> First<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, we muste chieflye accustome oure selues, to sustaine and suffer, the maners, wordes and Déedes of men: we shoulde not immediatelye speake doggedly or roughly vnto them: or be soone assailed with bitter anger, if they bring anye loathsomnesse vnto vs: but being (as it were) ignorant thereof, wée shoulde with Silence put it awaye, or giue it the slippe: for, tauntingly to bite or nippe againe, either to bée in a furie or rage, and that for a light offēce, is a most manifest signe of a very féeble and weake harted man. Secondlye, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> let vs subscribe vnto the iudgement and ready becke of others, that both we and they mighte haue one will to choose or to refuse: and that wée mighte couet togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther onely that thing, whiche they most gladlye doe desire: and shunne also
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:176849:67"/> al suche things as doe not delight them, but bringeth an occasion to the stirring vppe of Choler, euen (as it were) with loathsome euacuation and vomiting.</p>
                  <p>Thirdelye, wée muste also agrée vnto <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> them, both touching their desires, their workes, and good endeuoutes: and wée muste likewise for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sée to study vpon the matter, and vppon such businesse as they also doe take in hande: For, whereas there is disagréement and controuersie, either touching matters of Study or of other businesse, doubtlesse, there do they but a short while liue merily and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly togither.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, wée maye not vniustlye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> resiste anye manne, vnlesse iniurie bée muche offered vnto vs, eyther throughe making contention, eyther throughe brailing, detracting, or slaundering.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, we may not prefer oure selues <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> before others, nor esteeme of our selues better than others, either yet to be more worthy or noble, than we iustly doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue. Sixtly, we must giue that vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> whiche we woulde desire to oure
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:176849:68"/> selues. Wée may not dispraise or hinder them, althoughe it mighte redounde to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> oure owne commoditie. Seuenthly, wée must alwayes be prepared and in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse, that when time and place shall conueniently requyre, we maye then be seruiceable vnto others: for seruice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and friendly, being timely and well bestowed, procureth the loue of friendes: and beyng to the contrarie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, it purchaseth hatred and enmity. Other manners and customes, dayly vse and experience wil sufficiently minister, whyche is the Lady and Maistresse of all good things.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In mutuall Conference, what is beste required.</head>
                  <p>IN the mutuall Talke &amp; Conference of menne, eight rules of great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie,<note place="margin">In Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvvixt mē, eyght Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are to be euer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued and kepte.</note> or eight Vertues, are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued of vs: that is to saye, not to vse any speache, in the time of other mens wordes or speaches: But whilest they are yet speaking, to holde oure tongues,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:176849:68"/> and so to expecte the ende of his talke. And herevppon sprang that olde saying: Two men (differing in cause) maye sing togither: but not both alike in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their words: for the talk of one mā doth so hinder the speache of an other, that it cannot be perfectly or truely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. Also not to backebite any man, to the hinderance of his good name and fame, whether he be absent or present: for (amongest men) there is no greater thefte or robbery, than is the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of a mans good name and fame.</p>
                  <p>Manne hath nothing more noble and excellent (nexte after his soule and life) that he maye lose or forbeare, than hys good name and fame: and whiche béeing once loste (as sayth <hi>Ouid</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid.</note>) thou shalt bée nothing worth: that is, neuer after to be accompted of, or to be of any estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and credite. We must therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes foresée, what we do speake of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie manner, and that we do not nipping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inueigh against those that be present, neyther yet the friendes and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of such as be present.</p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:176849:69"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Speaches are firste to be ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red beefore they bee vttered.</note>We shoulde not speake anye thing, vnlesse we did firste premeditate y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same in our minds: and so weigh to what end and purpose it woulde be moste aptelye inclined: that is, whether the saying do properly tend vnto Follie or Wisedom: either whether it leaneth to do any hurt, or whether it will yéelde vnto profite. Also, let euery manne take héede, howe he doth tell or cary any newes, least hée be counted but a busie talker or a tatler: for he that is a teller of newes, is thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte to be but a trifler, a very lyar, and a blabbe. Wée maye not séeke after the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creates of others, and that for two spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall causes. The firste is, bycause that the mouthe whyche doeth reueale o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mennes secreates, is doubtlesse in verye euill case. And the seconde is, bicause suche as be séekers after se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creates, are commenlye to bée iudged Traytoures: that after they haue once knowne suche Secreates, they wyll then conspyre to doe some mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. <hi>Horace</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horace.</note> in hys Epistles coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth, saying after thys manner:
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:176849:69"/> Let euery man (sayth he) whether he be sober or drunke, conceale and kéepe se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete all suche things as are hidde and not disclosed: for he that babbleth out things which be secret, is thought to be worse thā a very théef: for secrets are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes of greater price, than are such things as be stolne of théeues and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Let no man therefore tel forthe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, than he hath iustly proued and known: for certainly, otherwise, he shal worthily be iudged to be but a false spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and a very lyar.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Hovv at all times vve should behaue our selues, when we talke with our betters.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ERasmus</hi> in his Dialogue of Talke doeth saye: As of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e as thou talkest with thy superiour and better, stande right and streyght vp, and let thine head be vncouered: and let thy countenaunce neyther be sadde nor frowning, ne yet shamelesse nor waywarde, no, neyther mouable or yet vnstayed: but alwayes
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:176849:70"/> wel ordered with a cheareful and séeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly modestie: hauing alwayes shamefast eyes, and that reuerently bent vpon him vnto whom thou speakest, with thy féet orderly ioined togither, and also holding still thyne handes. Stande not vpon one foote: neyther let thy fingers be vainely fimbling about any thing: neyther byte thou thy lippe, nor scratch thine heade, neyther yet picke thine eares. Thy gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (in lyke manner) is made vnto thée for comlynesse-sake: that the whole Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, countinaunce, gesture and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre of thy bodye, maye shewe forth a gentlemanlye modestie, and a ryght bashefull disposition or towardnesse to Vertue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The order of comelynesse, in walkyng abroade wyth others.</head>
                     <p>IF it so chaunce vnto vs, that wée do walke abroad: or in so walking, to haue some cōference with some other: we muste be instructed in nine sundrye
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:176849:70"/> sortes of maners. And the firste of them is, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in speaking, we must be courteous, faire spoken, mylde, and gentle. For, (as <hi>Plautus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Plaut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>▪</note> sayth:) A merry companyon in the way, is in steade of an easie wagon or Chariote, which is of rounde &amp; swifte passage: for it easeth a man of paine and wearisomnesse in the course of his time and iourney. And if wee séeme to be of baser state than he is with whom we do walk and talke, we must giue vnto him by the waye (as the maner is) the righte hande, or else goe something behynde hym: for, we may not goe before him, vnlesse we craue licence: neyther maye we goe faster, than reason requireth of vs, but to make haste very orderly and comely as <hi>Cicero</hi> in his <hi>Offices</hi> cōman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. In going, we may not be sprinckle thē that go néere vnto vs, or with vs: but we must so direct and order our féete and our steppes, that we do not bespot them with mire and dirte. We muste also speake wyth lowe and meane sounde of voyce, &amp; not with a loude or shrill noyse. Againe, we oughte to gyue place vnto
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:176849:71"/> such as we do méete in the waye: and in méeting of them, we may not crosse thē, least we touch y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bodyes one of another, as one Goate toucheth another with their hornes. Let vs reuerence suche as we doe méete, by giuing them the way: and after a more séemely maner, let vs also honour all those, vnto whom honor of right is due. In this wise (truely) we ought to salute all such as we do méete: for, in such maner to salute, is doubtlesse great courtesie, very godly, and therfore prayse worthye. Wherevnto <hi>Cato</hi> in times past gaue this counsell: Salute o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gently and willinglye. For, to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, is none other thing, than to wyshe health and welfare vnto another: and this truely doth chiefly become &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifye the state of an honest man. Vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reuerently thine heade vnto such as do méete with thée.<note place="margin">To salute, vvhat it is.</note> For in that, that a man doth so abase and humble himselfe, he thereby doth shew himselfe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly an inferiour vnto others. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing also, Christ himselfe did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, that we shoulde be lowlye in
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:176849:71"/> our owne eies, &amp; not in minde be proude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puffed vp, or swel in the vanitie of our mindes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>What is most seemely for vs, in the time of our myrth and pastime.</head>
                     <p>THe Time also is suche a thing, that it requireth hys <hi>Decorum:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Decorum</note> that is to say, his order and comelinesse: for we doe more offende at one time, than we do at another. And the time is of two sorts. It is eyther ioyful and prosperous: or else (to the contrarie) it is sorrowful, and not prosperous. If the tyme therefore shall be vnto thée fortunate and happy, a four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde <hi>Decorum</hi> or decencie therein is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be obserued and kept.</p>
                     <p>The first is, if fortune do ouermuch <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> smyle vpon our prosperitie, we may not therfore accordingly flatter too much our selues by our reioycing and gladnesse: least that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ōmonly wont to bée saide, be seene in vs, as <hi>Iuuenall</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iuuenal.</note> witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth saying: Mans minde knoweth not
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:176849:72"/> howe to kéepe measure in wealthe and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> prosperitie. Secondly, we ought not to deride or contemne another mā, whom Fortune (in comparison of our selues) fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth, not, as though we were more happie than they: for, that is but to brag and shew our selues high minded: which also is (as we wel knowe) a thing verye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> hateful in the presence of God. Thirdly, we must alwayes feare, and be careful, least Fortune should chaunge his course with vs: for she is more vnconstant thā the winde: and it is also sayde, howe she doth always stande vpon a tottering or tourning whéele, so that, she is neuer stayde or still abides in one state: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in olde time, a certaine Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher was alwayes woonte in his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and prosperitie, to be sorowful and heauie: truely knowing or foreséeing, that after such felicitie, aduersitie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōly foloweth. And again, whē fortune did frowne vpon him, he woulde great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then reioyce: hauing good experience, that after a sharpe showre, we shoulde haue calme and fayre weather: and after
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:176849:72"/> aduersitie, there should alwayes folowe prosperitie. Fourthly, we must giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> God most hartie thanks, that he hath graunted vnto vs suche prosperitie, and here to haue had at his hande, so good and happie successe. And that we séeme not to be vnthankefull vnto God: but in yéelding of thanks vnto him, it may the rather be a meane to allure him, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowe greater benefites vpon vs. Wée maye not forgette God, by reason of the happinesse of Fortune and of time, as those oft do which be in welfare and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity: but we ought to remember God with thankefulnesse of hart and minde, and to praye alwayes vnto him, that he will more and more encrease and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper that friendly countenance towards vs, which he hath so happily bestowed al readie vpon vs: or else with some small discommoditie to ende and chaunge the same.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:176849:73"/>
                     <head>What things are requisite in aduersitie and trouble.</head>
                     <p>BVt if at any time we shalbe distres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed wyth aduersitie and trouble: we muste be defended by the true rules of beautie and comelinesse.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The first is, how we may not despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately promise vnto our selues, that wée shall fall into Aduersitie, or neuer after attaine vnto Felicitie or good Fortune: but we must be of a valiaunt minde and courage, and truste to atteyne vnto bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prosperitie. And let vs comforte our selues with thys saying of <hi>Virgil:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> God (doubtlesse) will soone make an ende of these things.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondlie, against al aduersitie or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicitie, we oughte to séeke for comfort by good and godly counsayle: and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by our owne witte and industrie, or else to demaunde counsayle of others, that be more wise than we our selues.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we must remember God, by our reuerent going vnto hym with oure
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:176849:73"/> faithful and dayly prayers: and despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratelye by murmuring and cursed blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie against his highe maiestie and godhead, for such aduersities as we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently do here suffer: but we muste call vpon him with sure trust and confidēce, that he wil graciously shorten such mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune and trouble, and turne the same vnto our health, prosperity and welfare: and that he will also therevnto giue vs his grace, that we may patiently suffer, whatsoeuer trouble or aduersitie shall chaunce vnto vs, and that with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different and vpright minde.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, we must rather reioyce in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> our minds, than be discouraged, that the same aduersitie hath so chaunced vnto vs: and through which also we shall the rather merite to haue afterwardes from the hande of God a good and gracious rewarde: and to haue also driuen from vs the multitude of all our sinnes.</p>
                     <p>Fiftlye, we must staye oure mindes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> vpon good and sure hope: and that, if wée worthily suffer punishment for our sins and iniquities: <hi>the punishment</hi> (as <hi>Ouid</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ouid.</note>
                        <pb n="126" facs="tcp:176849:74"/> sayeth) <hi>which commeth by iust desarte, is so much the more to be borne withal: but such as commeth vnto vs vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or not deserued, is the rather to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and sorrowed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtely, we must accompte of our sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be men: and it therefore becōmeth not men to be discouraged or féeble min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by anye lighte or trifling aduersitie, but to be of a strong and valiant hearte, and of good courage.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>What is required of vs, in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and obeying of others.</head>
                     <p>IN doing also of our Duetie and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, we must alwayes be prudent and wise, that it maye the rather be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto them, vpon whome it is bestowed: least our trauell, our laboure, and our coste, be scoffed at and derided. And touching this matter, sixe things there are of vs to be obserued. We must sée before hande, that our s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ruice be profytable vnto them, vpon whome we
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:176849:74"/> doe bestowe our seruice: for, he that in seruice attempteth hurtefull and displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunte things, doth not only therby, not doe any good at all, or duetifull seruice: but rather bringeth with him, muche harme and destruction. It must therfore be both orderly done, and in due season, and at a conuenient time, for, benefites vnseasonable, or things bestowed out of due time, are not to be receyued or taken in such good part, as <hi>Erasmus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mus.</note>
                        <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> witnesseth: To offer fréely and of our owne accorde, and not to stay or tarye, vntill we be moued or called vnto: for, being therevnto constrayned throughe any crauing of pouertie, and so, to helpe and to do good: it then shal the rather ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, howe we doe iustlye deserue to haue but small commendation &amp; prayse. Therfore do the comō people say: That thing is very dearely boughte, which is attained vnto or purchased by much sute or by praiers. And although in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> things which we do promise, be of high value and price: yet may we not defer the performance of such promises:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:176849:75"/> For (in such things) fond delaying of the time, maketh the shew of our dueties to be both vnthankful and tedious. Due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and al maters of seruice, must wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly be done and spéedily, and not as is the maner of an Asse, which otherwhiles is enforced to drinke: neyther ought we to be as is the beaste <hi>Testudo,</hi> slouthfull or créeping in our attemptes: or as the <hi>Aceassei</hi> is,<note place="margin">Snaile. <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>ceassei.</hi>
                        </note> that gaseth vp for the Moone. Things should be as wel and faithfully done, as though the matter were in déed our owne: yea, and that more faithfully is our friendes matter to be executed or preferred than our owne: for then is she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed forth the brightnesse of oure fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true friendshippe. Thyngs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, or that ought to be done, shold be done eyther friendlye and courteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, or else fréelye omitted and let passe. For, suche Dueties or Seruices are they alwayes thoughte to bée, as the minde of the doer is alreadye bente. That seruice is thanke worthye, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is done from a thankefull and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling minde: but that whiche by enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:176849:75"/> is done, or against the wil, is vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye voyd of delyght, and not to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully taken. If through riches thyngs are to be done, we must do them so much the more franckely, largelye, and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfullye: For the grace of the former good tourne, perisheth and quite va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth awaye, vnlesse it be agayne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed or requited with some newe and louely benefite.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>What the Dueties are of a Magistrate or Officer.</head>
                     <p>IF we be called to Gouernemente, or to haue any charge of Office, to rule and gouerne others, or to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>séers amongst them: then verye néede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is, that we do excell in the Vertue of Wisedome: yea, in such a Wisdome chiefly, as is to be termed, a fourefolde Wisedome. And so we ought to behaue our selues, and to be such persons indéed, as our state truely requireth vs to be. We ought in such calling, to be muche
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:176849:76"/> more wise than others, ouer whome we séeme to haue authoritie. For great is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dishonestie to be aboue another in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or in aucthoritie, and not to bée the same in Wisdome and Prudēce. In whych high state, or excellencie of oure calling, neyther ought we to be hyghe minded or proudely puffed vp, and haue others in contempt in comparison of our selues, as that Souldiour did whom <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> speaketh of: but let vs rather fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this saying of <hi>Cice.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>icero.</note> that how much the more we be called vnto high degrée, so muche the more lowlye ought we to behaue our selues. And we ought more to séeke the profitte of others, than anye commoditie to our selues. For a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate or an Officer, doth execute the Office of a publike or common person. And it is required also of vs, that wée be not harmefull vnto the guiltlesse and innocent: ne yet ouermuch fauour suche as be offenders. Notwithstanding, in punishment, measure ought alwayes to be vsed: neyther shoulde the punishment be greater, than the faulte it selfe most
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:176849:76"/> iustelye deserueth, as <hi>Cicero</hi> sayth. And let the Gouernours themselues, be lyke vnto those laws, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which (both right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; iustly) they entēd to take punishmēt vpon others. And let vs here be carefull, how these tē vices folowing,<note place="margin">Ten vices to be ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, vvhat they ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> may be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> common wealth, or from such, as yet liue in the st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>te of subiection: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, the sin of falshode or vntruth: y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sin of spoyle &amp; robberie: the sin of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse, of enuy, of ambitiō, of backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bighting, periurie, negligēce, wrong, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sins of wickednes &amp; great mischief, as <hi>Plautus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Plautus.</note> in his Commedie <hi>Per,</hi> willeth &amp; cōmaundeth vs. Let vs thinke, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> things first reformed in our selues, do far better become vs, than those, ouer whiche we haue authoritie to commaunde: bycause oure owne faults shoulde sooner be espi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than the faultes of subiectes: as lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Poets</hi> in times paste haue for oure learning described. <hi>Ouid</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> in his <hi>Conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi> vnto <hi>Liuia Augusta</hi> sayeth: <hi>Those things are not comelye for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, whyche properlye doe belong vnto hyghe Magistrates: for
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:176849:77"/> vnto Magistrates, Superioritie doe chieflye belong. A Magistrate, both his eyes, his eares, and hys deedes are marked: neither can the voyce of a King once vttered, bee concealed or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</hi> Vnto which sentēce, doeth <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Claudianus</note> in these verses subscribe: <hi>Of this, wil I oftentimes warn thee, that thou cal to minde the order of thy life here in the middest of the worlde: bycause thy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are truely knowne vnto al nations: neyther can a kings vices be kept secrete at any time: for, the most high and clear light of the sunne, doth suffer nothing to be couered or hidde, but entreth into all darke places: yea, and Fame also sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth narrowly out, alsecrete caues and holes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:176849:77"/>
                  <head>There be also other Verses of the same <hi>Claudianus,</hi> whiche <hi>Beroaldus</hi> thinketh shoulde be written vpon Princes Gates, that is to say:</head>
                  <p>THou, whiche doest rule the Citizens, and the Fathers of the Citie: gyue counsaile vnto all menne, and not alone vnto thy selfe: neyther let thine own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings once trouble thee or moue thee: but let thy publike prayers be common vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al men. And if thou thinkest that any thing is meete to be obserued and kept: do it then firste thy selfe: and then is it the more fitte to be done of the people. Neither do they refuse the doings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when they once doe see the Authour himselfe, obey himself. For, al the whole world do folow the exāple of the King: neither can mās reason set forth such or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances &amp; Laws, as the life of the Ruler himselfe. For, the inconstāt &amp; wauering people, are alwayes changed, euen as the Prince himselfe is chaunged.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:176849:78"/>
                  <head>Howe Vertue or Honestie being once gotten, may be stablished and neuer againe lost.</head>
                  <p>VErtue or Honestie, being once kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and obtained, and that it be not at anye time remoued againe from vs, and that we doe not againe infecte oure selues with Vices: these thrée rules fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, are déeply to be ingrauen in our mindes: that as they were nailes and anchours, they might kéepe Vertue stil within vs, strengthen Honestie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme also in vs the vse of good conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and maners. First therefore, all such things as do annoy or hinder Honestie, are to be fled from and auoyded: all al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements vnto Vices, are to bée eschu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and all Delights and wicked plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, as surffetting, ryot, and ydlenesse. Herevpon <hi>Hermolaus Barbarus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>molaus <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>barus.</note> sayde: Belly cheare, softe and gay apparel, and fleshelye pleasures are to be shunned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways of him, which is desirous of praise. Secondlie, wée must not thinke of anye
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:176849:78"/> thing, neyther yet do any thing, saue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which is honest and agreable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Vertue. Let onely things whyche bée good and honest, be exercised and invred. Let all our workes labours, and cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, be applyed vnto that matter whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is imputed good and honest. So, at length it shall come to passe, that we stil accustoming oure selues vnto vertues, they shall be no lesse easie vnto vs, than if they were bred naturallye in vs. Wée ought therefore as muche to deteste Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as we woulde doe a vile Dogge, or venemous biting Serpent. Herevppon, <hi>Virgil</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> saide: Yea, of suche greate force is it to accustome oure selues from oure yong yeares in any thing. For, truelye, there is nothing of greater force, thā the daylye accustoming and exercising of a thing. Thirdely, some man peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will saye: Howe can a man eyther do or once muse at all times of good and honest things, whereas there is no man wise at all times: but the beste and wisest manne sometymes sléepeth and is negligent. Therefore, this thirde
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:176849:79"/> rule is, with al our possibilitie, might and power, to be euermore embraced: that is to wit, that we should be conuersant and liue only among suche as be Vertuous and Honest: and that we shoulde neuer conuey our selues out of their companye and felowship: as <hi>Cicero</hi> writeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, howe he neuer departed from that old mans company: namely <hi>Mutius Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uola.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mutius Sceuola.</note> For (doubtlesse) it is a wonderfull thing to be tolde, how much domesticall or daily familiaritie of men auaileth in maners. And whiche also in a certayne maner, both chaungeth, inuerteth, and al wholly altereth the naturall disposition of maners. Therefore, in times paste, it was thus writtē in the Psalmist: With the good,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>salm. 18.</note> thou shalte become good: &amp; with the frowarde thou shalt learne froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Therefore, we shal be honest, and so continue still in the same: euen so long time as we shall associate our selues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong such as be Vertuous and Honest.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:176849:79"/>
            <head>The Table of this present Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The first Chapiter, and the contents therof.</head>
               <item>WHat an honest life is, wherof it consisteth, and what it profiteth. Fol. <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Poet <hi>Lucillius,</hi> his description of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Fol. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The diuision of Vertue. Fol. <hi>8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The rewarde of Vertue, and of an honest life. Fol. <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The second Chapter.</head>
               <item>How an honest life and Vertue, are to bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned. Fol. <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Abstinence. Fol. <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Learning, of Knowledge, and of Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Fol. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whether Vertue maye bee attained wythoute Learning. Fol. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Exercise. Fol. <hi>32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The exercise of our Knowlege, for the obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Vertue. Fol. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The third Chapiter.</head>
               <item>What comelinesse, and what Vertue and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie is of man to bee kepte in euerye time
<pb facs="tcp:176849:80"/> and age. Fol. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He that wil teach and rule himselfe honestly, must keepe sixe precepts. Fol. <hi>42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Maners and Vertues of sundrye times and ages. Fol. <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Infancie. Fol. <hi>52</hi> Of Childhoode. Fol. <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Youth. Fal. <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The dueties of Yong men. Fol. <hi>57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Yong mans state. Fol, <hi>58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Howe Yong men are to be trained vp of their parents &amp; Maisters, to Vertue and Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie. Fol. <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Instruction consisteth in sixe preceptes. Fol. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Warning. Fol. <hi>68</hi> Of Promise. Fol. <hi>69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Praise and Threatning. Fol. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the duties of Yongmen. Fol. <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Mans age. Fol. <hi>64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the honest life of Man. Fol. <hi>65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of olde Age. Fol. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <item>What honestie beste becommeth vs, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes God and men. Fol. <hi>71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What beste becommeth vs to doe towardes
<pb facs="tcp:176849:80"/> Almightie God. Fol. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What becommeth vs to doe towardes menne. Fol. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What oure duetie is, towardes oure Countrey. Fol. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What oure duetie is towardes oure Parentes. Fol. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What successe they haue had, which haue bin disobedient to their Parents. Fol. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What best becōmeth vs, towards our Schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maisters and Teachers. Fol. <hi>79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of those which haue dishonored their Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Teachers. Fol. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Duties towards Maisters. Fol. <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What duties we doe owe, towardes oure Alies and Kinsfolkes. Fol. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of duties towardes oure friendes. Fol. <hi>85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Oure duties towardes our equalles or fellowes. Fol. <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of duties towards women. Fol. <hi>94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of duties towards Forrainers and Strangers. Fol. <hi>96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Duties towardes our Enimies. Fol. <hi>100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Duties towards our Maisters whome we doe serue. Fol. <hi>102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Duties towards Magistrates. Fol. <hi>104</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:176849:81"/>
               <head>The fifte Chapter.</head>
               <item>What beste beseemeth all degrees of men, in euery place and time. Fol. <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What is comely at a Banquet. Fol. <hi>108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>We must wel iudge with our selues whilest we be drinking, sixe preceptes of Vertue and Honestie to be alwayes obserued. Fol. <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Howe sober communication beste beseemeth good company. Fol. <hi>111</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In mutuall conference, what is beste requyred. Fol. <hi>114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How at al times we should behaue our selues towards our betters. Fol. <hi>117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The order of comelinesse, in walking abroade with others. Fol. <hi>118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What is seemely for vs, in the time of oure myrth and pastime. Fol. <hi>121</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What things are requisite in time of aduersity and trouble. Fol. <hi>124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What is required of vs, in seruing and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of others. Fol. <hi>126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the duties are of a Magistrate or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. Fol. <hi>129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Vertue or Honestie once gotten, maye be stablished, &amp; neuer againe lost. Fol. <hi>134</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>